<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pyrotechnia or, A discourse of artificiall fire-works in which the true grounds of that art are plainly and perspicuously laid downe: together with sundry such motions, both straight and circular, performed by the helpe of fire, as are not to be found in any other discourse of this kind, extant in any language. VVhereunto is annexed a short treatise of geometrie, contayning certaine definitions and problemes, for the mensuration of superficies and sollids, with tables for the square root to 25000, and the cubick root to 10000 latus, wherein all roots under those numbers are extracted onely by ocular inspection. VVritten by Iohn Babington gunner, and student in the mathematicks.</title>
            <author>Babington, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B11293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1099</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106893</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842602</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842602</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177062</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B11293)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177062)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 777:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pyrotechnia or, A discourse of artificiall fire-works in which the true grounds of that art are plainly and perspicuously laid downe: together with sundry such motions, both straight and circular, performed by the helpe of fire, as are not to be found in any other discourse of this kind, extant in any language. VVhereunto is annexed a short treatise of geometrie, contayning certaine definitions and problemes, for the mensuration of superficies and sollids, with tables for the square root to 25000, and the cubick root to 10000 latus, wherein all roots under those numbers are extracted onely by ocular inspection. VVritten by Iohn Babington gunner, and student in the mathematicks.</title>
                  <author>Babington, John.</author>
                  <author>Droeshout, John, d. 1652, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 72; [4], 80, 200 p., [2] folded plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper, for Ralph Mab,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXXXV. [1635]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an additional title page, engraved, signed "Io Droeshout scul": Pyrotechnia or a discourse of artificiall fire workes for pleasure ..</note>
                  <note>"A short treatise of geometrie" has separate dated title page, pagination, and register. It was also issued separately (STC 1100).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Lacking "A short treatise of geometrie".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fireworks --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Geometry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mensuration --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Roots, Numerical --  Tables.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177062:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177062:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177062:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177062:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177062:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177062:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PYROTECHNIA OR, A DISCOVRSE OF ARTIFICIALL <hi>FIRE-WORKS:</hi> In which the true Grounds of that Art are plainly <hi>and perſpicuouſly laid downe:</hi> Together with ſundry ſuch Motions, both <hi>Straight</hi> and <hi>Circular, performed by the helpe of Fire, as are not</hi> to be found in any other Diſcourſe of this kind, <hi>Extant in any Language.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhereunto is annexed a ſhort TREATISE of <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrie, contayning certaine</hi> Definitions <hi>and</hi> Problemes, for the Menſuration of <hi>Superficies</hi> and <hi>Sollids,</hi> with <hi>Tables</hi> for the Square Root to 25000, and the Cubick Root to 10000 <hi>Latus, wherein all Roots under thoſe Numbers are extracted onely by Ocular Inſpection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by <hi>John Babington</hi> Gunner, and Student <hi>in the</hi> MATHEMATICKS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by THOMAS HARPER, for RALPH MAB, MDCXXXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:177062:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177062:4"/>
            <head>A Table of the Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 1</hi> HOw to make all ſorts of moulds in a true proportion with the Rollers, and drift. <hi>Page 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2</hi> How to make your Coffines of paper. <hi>p. 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3</hi> How you ſhall choake a Rocket. <hi>idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4</hi> The manner of driving a Rocket, with the inſtruments belonging to the ſame. <hi>p. 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5</hi> The manner of heading a Rocket, with the order of capping the ſame. <hi>p. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6</hi> The manner of finiſhing a Rocket. <hi>p. 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 7</hi> The manner of fyring Rockets, with the deſcription of a ſtaffe for fyring of them. <hi>p. 10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 8</hi> Divers compoſitions for ſtarres. <hi>p. 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 9</hi> The manner of making the beſt ſort of ſtarres. <hi>p. 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 10</hi> The manner of making ſilver and golden raine. <hi>p. 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 11</hi> How to make fiſgigs which ſome call Serpents. <hi>idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 12</hi> How to make the reports or breakers. <hi>p. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 13</hi> How to make a Runner on the Line. <hi>p. 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 41</hi> The manner of firing your Runner. <hi>p. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 15</hi> How to compoſe a Wheele. <hi>p. 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 16</hi> How to make a ground Wheele. <hi>p. 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 17</hi> Another manner of ground Wheeles. <hi>p. 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 18</hi> The manner of making a fixed Wheele which ſhall give divers reports. <hi>p. 22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 19</hi> How to make a fixed Wheele which ſhall caſt forth many Rockets into the Aire. <hi>idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 20</hi> How to make a fixed Wheele which ſhall caſt forth divers fiſgigs, and likewiſe as many reports. <hi>p. 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 21</hi> The manner of making a Wheele to runne two wayes, which is forward and backward. <hi>idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 22</hi> The manner of compoſing a Wheele, which having finiſhed his revolution, ſhall repreſent a Coat of Armes. <hi>p. 25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 23</hi> How to repreſent a Coat of Armes in fire which having burnt a ſmall while, the ſaid Coat ſhal appeare in perfect colours, and ſhal continue ſo a long while. <hi>p. 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 24</hi> How to repreſent an antick dance by the helpe of fire, which ſhall moove in a circular forme. <hi>p. 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 25</hi> Another way for making an antick dance which is not ſo violent as the former, <hi>p. 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 26</hi> How to compoſe a Caſtle of fire-worke, with the manner of placing the works in a true order, <hi>idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 27</hi> How to repreſent divers motions in a Caſtle of Fire-worke. <hi>p. 30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 28</hi> Another way to performe the ſame Motions, and will not be ſo violent as the former. <hi>p. 34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 29</hi> How to repreſent the forme of an Army of an hundred men marching, which ſhall preſent and fire at on certaine place appointed. <hi>idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 30</hi> How to repreſent Muſique playing (by the helpe of fire) with anticks dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing. <hi>p. 36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 31</hi> How to make a Dragon or any other creature run on the line, by the helpe of fire. <hi>idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 32</hi> Another way for making a fiery Dragon to paſſe on the line without the helpe of fire. <hi>p. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 33</hi> How to repreſent Saint <hi>George</hi> fighting with a Dragon on the line, <hi>p. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 34</hi> How to make a trunke of fire, which ſhall caſt forth divers fire-balls. <hi>p. 41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 35</hi> The manner of making a Club which ſhall caſt forth divers ſmall workes or fiſgigs. <hi>p. 42</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:177062:5"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 36</hi> Another ſort of club, which being fired, ſhall give many reports. <hi>p. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 37</hi> Another which I call Iacke in a boxe. <hi>p. 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 38</hi> How to repreſent the ſphere moving in the ayre, without any other ſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 39</hi> How to repreſent the sphere, with divers circles, ſome moveable, others fixed. <hi>p. 46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 40</hi> How to make a halfe moone of rockets appeare in the ayre. <hi>p. 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 41</hi> How to make a caſe of rockets to riſe at once. <hi>Idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 42</hi> How to make letters or any other figure appeare in the ayre, after the ſpending of a rocket. <hi>p. 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 43</hi> How to repreſent a figure of the Sun, caſting forth his beames in fire. <hi>Idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 44</hi> How to make a rocket, which firing it out of your hand, ſhall continually be in agitation, on the ground ſometimes, and other whiles about in the ayre. <hi>p. 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 45</hi> How to make a ball which ſhall be in continuall agitation on the ground, till the fire be conſumed. <hi>p. 51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 46</hi> How to make another ſort of bals for the ground, which will continue a long while in their motion. <hi>Idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 47</hi> How to make a Dragon iſſuing out of a Cave, which ſhal caſt out much fire. <hi>p. 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 48</hi> How to make two Dragons to meet each other from ſeverall Caves, which ſhal ſend forth their fire to each other with great violence. <hi>Idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 49</hi> How to make a bucklar, which ſhall caſt forth a hundred Fiſgigs, every one making his report. <hi>p. 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 50</hi> How to make the Curtlax, Cimiter, or Fauchion. <hi>p. 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 51</hi> How to make a water ball which ſhall burne on the water with great vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. <hi>Idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 52</hi> A water ball which ſhall ſhoot forth many reports. <hi>p. 56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 53</hi> How to make a water ball, which after a certaine time of firing, ſhall caſt forth divers rockets into the ayre. <hi>p. 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 54</hi> Another ſort of water ball, which ſhall caſt forth rockets at two ſundry times, and after it is finiſhed, ſhall give a great report. <hi>p. 58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 55</hi> Another ſort of bal, with iron chambers, every one caſting forth a ſmal bal. <hi>p. 60</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 56</hi> The proportions of the morter piece. <hi>p 61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 57</hi> How to make a ball for the Morter piece, which ſhall caſt forth a great ſhower of ſtarres at the breaking. <hi>Idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 58</hi> Another ſort of ball for the morter piece, which ſhall caſt forth divers Rockets in the ayre. <hi>p. 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 59</hi> How to compoſe a ſhip of fire-worke, which being once fired, divers motions ſhall preſent themſelves. <hi>p 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 60</hi> How to make the Syren or Mermaid playing on the water. <hi>Idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 61</hi> How to repreſent a Dragon iſſuing out of a Caſtle, which ſhall ſwim through the water, and be encountred by a horſeman from the ſhoare. <hi>p. 66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 62</hi> An order for a generall piece of fire-worke for land, and is for the pleaſure of a Prince, or ſome great perſonage <hi>p. 67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 63</hi> An other order for a generall worke, and is to be acted on the water. <hi>p. 68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 64</hi> The uſe of certaine engines for trying the goodneſſe or ſtrength of powder. <hi>p. 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 65</hi> The manner of making one of the aforeſaid engines. <hi>Idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 66</hi> Another engine for the ſame. <hi>p. 71</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 67</hi> A third Engine for the ſame. <hi>Idem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 68</hi> Another Engine for trying the ſtrength of powder by water. <hi>p. 27</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177062:5"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE, THE EARLE OF <hi>Newport,</hi> Maſter of his Majeſties Ordnance, my ſingular good Lord.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not induced to preſent this Treatiſe to your Lordſhip for any worth that is either in it, or in my ſelfe, the Author of it; the thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſmall moment, and my ſelfe of as little account: but your Lordſhips ſingular clemency to all, and your Honourable favour vouchſafed to me in particular, hath made me thus bold, and hath cauſed me thus farre to preſume. I have beene for certaine yeeres paſt, and ſo at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent am, one of the inferiour Gunners of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie; and ever ſince I held that place, I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to gaine ſuch skill and experience, as I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed moſt requiſite for that ſervice. And to that end I have beſtowed ſome time and expence, as my occaſions and ability would permit, in the practiſe of <hi>Artillery</hi> and <hi>Fire-workes,</hi> wherein though I have chiefly aymed at ſuch concluſions as might be uſefull againſt an enemy in the <hi>field,</hi> yet theſe <hi>halcyon</hi> dayes of peace and tranquility, which
<pb facs="tcp:177062:6"/> through the goodneſſe of God we have ſo long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, have given mee occaſion to invent and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe ſuch alſo as theſe following; which howſoever they may ſeeme to ſerve onely for delight and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, yet as by the handling of theſe there may bee gained knowledge in the natures and operations of the ſeverall ingredients and their compoſitions; ſo the due conſideration of the ordering of them may excite and ſtirre up in an ingenious minde, ſundry inventions more ſerviceable in times of warre. Now becauſe your Lordſhip hath of late, by the gratious providence of the Almighty, for your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary wiſedome and worth, beene advanced to that eminent place, upon which I have ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance, and to which I ſtand obliged by my ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall ſervice (to which alſo all workes of <hi>Pyrotech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> may ſeeme to have relation) I hold it my boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den duty to preſent theſe firſt fruits of my labours to your Honour, as an unfayned teſtimony, and an undoubted evidence of my faithfull obſervance, and ſingular reſpect to your Lordſhip: which if you ſhall be pleaſed to take into your ſpecial Patronage and protection, I ſhall be in good hope to be freed both from the venomous tooth of <hi>Momus,</hi> and from the malevolent aſpect of <hi>Zoilus,</hi> and from the poyſoned breath and ſtinging of the reſt of that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous brood, and ſhall alwaies remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in all dutifull obſervance, <hi>IOHN BABINGTON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177062:6"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving for mine owne private recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſpent ſome vacant houres in the ſtudy and contemplation of thoſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall <hi>Fire-works</hi> which are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of in the enſuing Treatiſe; J held it requiſite for my further and better ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as any opportunity did offer it ſelfe, to make expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment of ſome of the particularities there ſet downe; and I did accordingly now and then bring into <hi>Act</hi> that whereof before I had but a meere <hi>Notion,</hi> and the bare and naked <hi>Theorie:</hi> which becauſe it could not be done ſo privately, but that of neceſsity ſometimes it would come to the view of others; by that meanes it is come to paſſe, that more notice than J was ever wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to, hath beene taken, that J have beſtowed ſome thoughts upon that ſubiect, and taken more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary paines in it. And not ſo onely, but thereupon alſo ſome of my intimate friends and acquaintance, who have a ſpeciall intreſt in me, have beene very inſtant and urgent with me that J would make my labours more publike, and communicate them to the world, by committing them to the Preſſe: whereto though J was
<pb facs="tcp:177062:7"/> a long while utterly unwilling, as being conſcious to my ſelfe of mine owne inability and inſufficiency to deviſe and contrive any thing worthy to come to ſuch publike view, yet their importunity hath at laſt ſo farre pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with me, that thoſe rude and unpoliſhed lines are now like to ſee the Sunne; and to come abroad to be ſcanned and cenſured by others. Jf thou ſhalt looke upon them with a faire and favourable eye, I ſhall bee encouraged to beſtow my paines upon ſome other thing, which may happily give thee more content, and in the meane while ſhall reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy true friend and well-willer, IOHN BABINGTON, Gunner.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:177062:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>In laudem Authoris IOANNIS BABINGTON</hi> Amici &amp; in Arte Matheſios celeberrima Socii.</head>
            <l>THe pleaſant object of cloſe ardent Bowres,</l>
            <l>Envelloped with <hi>Florae's</hi> fragrant flowres,</l>
            <l>The goodly Proſpect of Skie-kiſsing Hils,</l>
            <l>Or fertile Plaines vein'd ore with purling Rils:</l>
            <l>More raviſh not my ſences with delight,</l>
            <l>Then doth thy <hi>Pyrotechnie.</hi> Many write</l>
            <l>Of Arts in themſelves worthy, but their worth</l>
            <l>Is much impairde by thoſe that ſet them forth,</l>
            <l>Wholly unskill'd in <hi>Megathologie,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The very ſoule of each deepe Myſterie.</l>
            <l>I wiſh ſuch ſhallow men would meddle leſſe,</l>
            <l>And with their ſenſeleſſe ſtuffe not cloy the Preſſe.</l>
            <l>All ſuch his Schoole to paſſe by <hi>Plato</hi> wilde</l>
            <l>In beautifull Geometrie not skild.</l>
            <l>Well haſt thou then my Friend expreſt thy Art,</l>
            <l>Since this rare Science hath the greater part</l>
            <l>Shar'd in thy Worke, giving it winged fire,</l>
            <l>To mount it up-aloft, and deck the ayre</l>
            <l>With ſplendent ſtars, ſilver and golden ſhowers;</l>
            <l>Theſe are th'effects of <hi>Mathematick</hi> powers:</l>
            <l>Which crown their <hi>Authors</hi> temples, not with bayes,</l>
            <l>But with a wreath of ſtars and fulgent rayes.</l>
            <l>Fairly goe on, thy ſelfe ſuch <hi>Trophies</hi> reare,</l>
            <l>That neither <hi>Time</hi> not <hi>Envie</hi> may outweare:</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Stutevill. Philomathes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:177062:8"/>
            <head>Vnto his worthy Friend, and induſtrious Artiſt, Maſter IOHN BABINGTON.</head>
            <l>VVHen as <hi>I</hi> did thy Booke by chance eſpie,</l>
            <l>With divers figures grac't, moſt curiouſly</l>
            <l>Contriu'd, all new, and of thine own invention,</l>
            <l>With ſundry Engines made by iuſt proportion:</l>
            <l>I did admire thy skill, thy active braine,</l>
            <l>Whereby thoſe things thou didſt ſo well attaine:</l>
            <l>Juſtly I might, for of no Nation yet,</l>
            <l>There's any hath this path ſo fully beat;</l>
            <l>Nor laid thoſe grounds that thou haſt done, whereby</l>
            <l>We might attaine to things that tend ſo high.</l>
            <l>For ſenceleſſe things with life thou ſeem'ſt to fill,</l>
            <l>Making them wondred at by common skill.</l>
            <l>Thou ſundry doubts unfold'ſt, and with much eaſe,</l>
            <l>Thou teacheſt us to meaſure Land and Seas.</l>
            <l>When as I thought on theſe, and knew how rare</l>
            <l>Men thus addicted, and thus given were,</l>
            <l>My mind, my hand, my hand did force my pen,</l>
            <l>T' offer my mite of thankes 'mongst other men.</l>
            <l>Accept it then, and let it no leſſe bee</l>
            <l>Pleaſing, then greater gifts are unto thee.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy truly affectionate, and wel-wiſhing Friend,</hi> John Bate.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:177062:8"/>
            <head>In commendations of his worthy Friend Maſter <hi>John Babington</hi> Gentleman.</head>
            <l>I f I were worthy to extoll the Name</l>
            <l>O f him that ſpends the 'Elixer of his ſpirits,</l>
            <l>H ow rare definde, I ſhould ſet forth the ſame,</l>
            <l>N ere ſhould I flinch; for why thy great demerits</l>
            <l>B ravely ſhould arme me boldly to oppoſe</l>
            <l>A gainſt thy Criticks and back-biting foes,</l>
            <l>B rave man of worth proceed: the rareſt wits,</l>
            <l>I f thy rare Worke doe come but in their view,</l>
            <l>N ere doubt, but they as ſoone as God permits,</l>
            <l>G reat love and aid will then expreſſe to you,</l>
            <l>T hat ſpends your time, ſpirits, and great expence</l>
            <l>O n Countries good for love, not recompence.</l>
            <l>N ow tell me thou that haſt a Tallent lent,</l>
            <l>Which was receiv'd from <hi>God Omnipotent,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And hor'dſt it up, burying it with thy Name,</l>
            <l>It there takes Period, ending with thy frame.</l>
            <l>When this my Authors fame, I iuſt preſage,</l>
            <l>Shall flouriſh ſtill, and not weare out with age.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Friend IOHN HICKS, <hi>alias Bridghampton</hi> Gunner.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:177062:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177062:9"/>
            <head>A Treatiſe of ARTIFICIALL FIRE-WORKS, moſt of them being invented and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the Author.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER I.</hi> How to make all ſorts of moulds, in a true proportion, with the Rowlers and Drifts.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I may ſet downe the true procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in Fireworkes, it is requiſite in the firſt place to lay downe the true order and forme of making all ſorts of moulds, aſwell greater as leſſe: and to proceed, you muſt get of the beſt drie Box you can finde; if not, of ſome other tough wood, as Crabbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, Holly, or ſuch like wood, which when you have provided according to your ſize you meane to uſe, it behoveth in the next place to be known, of what diameter you will have the heighth of your bore, and from thence all the reſt is derived: For example, I deſire to have one bored of an inch high, which I get bored by ſome Turner; and to know of what length it muſt be, I take for the ſayd length ſix diameters of the bore, which maketh ſix inches, and for the thickneſſe it ought to be halfe a diameter on each ſide, ſo that being turned true round, it contaynes two inches in diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Then have you to provide a bottome, which is to be fitted in ſuch ſort as you ſee deſcribed in this figure: the proportions heerafter follow.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>is the foot of the mould, and is in heighth two diameters, which muſt bee two inches; and one diameter and</hi> ¼ <hi>in breadth, whether it bee ſquare or round.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>ſerveth only for a ſtay, and muſt ariſe one inch into the mould, which is one diameter, and ſo proportionall in all other ſorts.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>is for the mouth of the rocket, and is in diameter</hi> ⅔ <hi>of the bore; ſo ſetting one foot of the compaſſes in the center, deſcribe the arch, which is the full heighth required.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177062:10"/>
                  <item>
                     <figure>
                        <head>fig 1</head>
                        <figDesc>diagram of a mold, roller, and drift used for fireworks</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:177062:10"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>E E ſerveth for the paper being rowled, and is</hi> ⅙ <hi>part of the diameter on each ſide:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>F F is the thickneſſe of the mould, which is halfe the diameter of the bore, that is in this place halfe an inch.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>F G the length of the mould, which is ſix diameters.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>D the length and bigneſſe of the needle, which is</hi> ⅔ <hi>the length of the mould, and bigneſſe to be</hi> ⅙ <hi>of the diameter of the bore at the bottom, and ſow taper to the top.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>When you have provided your mould according to your deſire, then you are to fit your rowler, which muſt be two third parts of the diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the bore of the ſayd mould, and the length thereof to bee ſix inches longer than your mould, which is for the roling of your paper, and is deſcribed by the letter A in this ſecond figure, with a hole to be bored in the bottom to receive a wyer, which muſt bee faſtned in another peece of wood ſomewhat ſhorter, which is to take out at pleaſure, as you may ſee deſcribed by the letter D: there is required no proportion of length for this ſhort peece; only it ſufficeth if it be but ſo long as a man may well hold it in his hand; the uſe hereafter ſhall be more plainly deſcribed when I come to ſpeake of the order of making the coffins; which ſhall be in the next Chapter. When you have fitted your rocket according to this direction, proceed to the making of your rammers, (or more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly called drifts) which muſt bee alwayes two at the leaſt to, each mould, and as your mould increaſes in largeneſſe, ſo muſt you have more rammers, by reaſon of the largeneſſe of the taper needle: the manner and form you may ſee deſcribed by the letters B C.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>B is the hollow rammer, and hath a hole in it anſwerable to the length and bigneſſe of the taper needle, as appeareth in that figure. It muſt be a ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter leſſe than the rowler, becauſe that otherwiſe in putting it in, you will put down the paper, which is very prejudiciall to your rocket.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The other rammer is not halfe ſo long, and is ſad, that when you have beaten to the top of the needle, you make uſe of it: it is deſcribed by the letter C.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>When you have fitted your rammers, you muſt provide a peece of Box made after the form as you ſee deſcribed; which muſt ſerve to make your large coffins to put the work which you intend, on the head of your rockets. It is deſcribed by the letter F, as in the figure is manifeſt.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The letters E E ſhew the diameter, which is the juſt bigneſſe of your roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, and muſt be ſo in all ſizes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>G G ſhewes the largenſſe of the coffin, and muſt bee two diameters, which in this figure is two inches.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>H H H H ſhewes the length of the coffin, which ought to bee two diameters of your rocket, which in this place is two inches; but we are not tied to that ſo preciſely; for we are to alter that according to the works which we put therein.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:177062:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> How to make your coffins of paper.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OW having explained the manner and forme of the moulds, with the reſt of the dependants, I come now to ſhew the uſe of them in their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall orders: and firſt for the uſe of the rowler, which is deſcribed by the letter A.</p>
               <p>You muſt provide ſome good ſtrong paper, as old Law books, which are both ſtrong and large; and cut out your ſizes of paper for your work: now to know what length your paper muſt bee, let it bee alwayes the length of your mould: ſo ſhall you have one diameter left above the mould, the uſe whereof ſhall be ſhewn in his proper place. Now having provided your paper in length ready, take your rowler, and one length of paper, and begin to rowle; when you have rowled one ſheet, you muſt have a board to rowle it with (the board is marked in the ſecond figure;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Figure</hi> 2. G.</note>) which muſt be done in this manner: you muſt hold the rowler in your left hand, and with your right hold the board; then lay down your rowler upon ſome ſmooth cheſt, or table, or ſuch like; which when you have done, lay on your board, and rowle it very hard, only one way; which having done, rowle another length, and ſo proceed in row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling between every ſheet, till you have rowled on ſo much as will fill the mould very ſtraight; when you have ſo done, draw forth your rowler one diameter, which in this place is one inch; and then take the other part of the rowler, which is ſhort, and marked with D, and put it in as you ſee deſcribed; and there have you a place left for the choaking of your rocket, of which we come now to ſpeak:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> How you ſhall choak a rocket.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen you come to choak your rocket, you muſt have a ring to ſcrew into ſome poſt, at which you muſt tie your cord, which muſt be bigger or leſſer, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the bigneſſe of your rocket, by reaſon that a ſmall cord will not choak a great rocket for want of ſtrength; and again, a great cord will not ſerve for a ſmall, in regard that it will make too great a choak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſo that you muſt have a bigger and leſſe; which when you have ſo provided, tying one end to the ring, you muſt about a yard off tie a ſtick, in faſhion of a handle for a ſwing, which muſt bee ſtrong, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that it muſt beare the whole weight of the body, (the letter G in the ſecond figure expreſſeth the ſame;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Figure</hi> 2. K.</note>) which when you have provided,
<pb facs="tcp:177062:11"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>
                        <hi>fig</hi> 2</head>
                     <figDesc>diagram of making a coffin of paper for fireworks</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:177062:12"/> put the ſticke betweene your legges, and winde the cord about the roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket caſe in the place appointed, which is betweene the long rowler and the ſhort, when you have ſo done, girt it by degrees, ever turning your rouler, to the end it may come together more cloſe and neat (the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is expreſſed in the third figure, by the letter K) ſo when you have choaked it ſufficiently, draw forth your ſhort rowler, and where your choaking is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Figure</hi> 3. K.</note> tye it about with ſtrong packthred; and ſo drawing forth your rowler, you have a coffin ready to be filled when occaſion ſerveth, the forme whereof followeth. And becauſe the choaking of a rocket is very laborious and dangerous, in regard of the breaking of the cord, which often hapneth; I haue therefore invented a certaine Engine, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a childe may choake the ſtrongeſt rocket. The parts of it are a ſcrew moving a wheele, on the axeltree of which is faſtened your cord for choaking, with the other end of the cord faſtened to a ſtaple on the ſame boord:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Figure</hi> 3. B. C.</note> the forme whereof you ſhall finde deſcribed in the third figure, by the letter B. C.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Figure</hi> 3.</note>A <hi>Js the coffin of a Rocket wholly finiſhed, with his choaking.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>The forme of an Engine for choaking a Rocket.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>The mannner of uſing the Engine.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F <hi>Is a meaſure made of horne or latten.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G <hi>Is a funnell with a handle to fill ſmall Rockets, and other ſmall works.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>H <hi>Is a fine ſearce, with a receiver to ſearce your ingredients.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I <hi>Is a morter to meale your powder, and your other ingredients, which muſt be of wood, with a peſtle.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Having deſcribed the order and formes of all things neceſſary to the making of a rocket, it reſteth now that we know the manner of driving it, as alſo what ingredients are moſt proper for every ſize.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The manner of driving a Rocket, with the inſtruments belonging to the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen you have finiſhed your coffin of paper, take it, and with your hollow rammer force it downe cloſe into your mould, which when you have done, ſtrike two or three ſmart blowes to ſettle the paper into his right forme: which being done, you muſt begin to fill your coffin, in doing whereof, you muſt have a great care, alwaies providing a meaſure, which may containe 1/20, part of your whole Rocket; ſo by that meanes you ſhall not faile, but every Rocket ſhall have a true proportion alike; as for Example, I have a coffin, which being filled, will hold an ounce of mixture or ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts. I take the twentieth part, and when I finde what quantity it is, I make a meaſure of horne, which ſhall containe ſo much, and then I beginne to fill my coffin with one meaſure at a time, and putting in my
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177062:12"/> rammer, ſtrike foure or five ſmart blowes with a good ſtrong mallet,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Figure</hi> 3. M.</note> and then I fill another meaſure, and ſtrike againe, ſo I continue till I come to the top of the needle, then I take the ſad rammer, and ſo continue with it, till I come to the top of the mould: now the paper which is above the top of the mould, muſt be turned downe, and beaten hard down, which being done, the Rocket is finiſhed from the mould; which force out, with as much eaſe as you can, for the leſſe you force it (being filled, and the needle taken out) the better it is, for knocking looſens the powder, and ſo cauſes the Rocket to faile: now it reſts to know the receits proper for every ſort of Rockets.</p>
               <q>And firſt for Rockets of one ounce,<note place="margin">The ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents for ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Rockets.</note> you may take only powder duſt being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fine ſearced; which riſes very ſwift, but carries no taile of fire with it, and often times breakes, unleſſe they be very thicke of paper: but the beſt and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt way is, to allay your powder with coale duſt being well ſearced, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes a more glorious ſhew; and you may uſe it at your diſcretion. The ordinary allay for ſmall Rockets is, <hi>1</hi> l. of powder, two ℥. of coale duſt, which ſerves till you come to Rockets of foure ounces, then muſt you take to every <hi>1</hi> l. of powder 2½ ℥ of coleduſt, continuing that quantity till you come to Rockets of tenne ounces, and from tenne to ſixteene ounces, which is one pound: your allay muſt be to one pound of powder, three ounces of coale.</q>
               <p>Now when you have provided your powder, you muſt firſt meale it, and then ſcarce it, ſo that it may be free from any corne though never ſo ſmall. Likewiſe take good dry coale, well burnt, and beat it to duſt, ſearcing it very fine, which when you have done, mixe them according as your occaſion ſerveth, and as your directions are.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The manner of heading a Rocket, with the order of capping it.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow we come to ſhew the manner of heading a Roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, in which we are to uſe our thicke Roler, ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſecond figure, and marked with F. Vpon which you muſt role ſome paper or fine paſt-board, and paſt it ſo that it may bee very cloſe, and then choake it at the length of the thicker part, ſo that it may come cloſe to your ſticke in the leſſer part, which will fit to be tyed to the top of your Rocket, ſo ſhall you have a coffine to put in your workes, which muſt bee of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſorts. That being done, you muſt provide Taper caps, which muſt be adjoyned to the top of the large coffin. The uſe of them is to keepe in your workes, and to cauſe them to pierce the ayre more ſwiftly. The manner of making theſe caps, is, to take a paire of Compaſſes, and deſcribe a circle in paſtboard, then cut it forth with a paire of ſheeres, and that ſhall make two cappes, being cut in the middle, and turned one corner under the other, and ſo paſted; and let them ſo paſted, be put in a napkin
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177062:13"/> preſſe till they be dry, and when they be dry, cut out a ſemicircle in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which ſhall fit round about the ſaid cap, and ſhall ſerve to paſte on the cap to the coffin: the forme whereof is expreſſed in the fourth figure, by the figure 14. and 15. ſo have you all things ready to the finiſhing of your Rocket, which muſt be done as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> The manner of finiſhing a Rocket.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen your Rocket is driuen, as I have ſhewed you, with the paper turned downe, you ſhall firſt prime it, which muſt be with cotton wicke made for the ſaid purpoſe, which you ſhall put up into the vent, leaving a peece to hang lower than the mouth of your Rocket, by three or foure inches, which being done, tye a piece of paper over the mouth, to the end it fall not out: now having primed your Rocket, you may proceede to the heading of it, and that is done after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Take your Rocket, and on the head (where I told you, you ſhould turne downe the paper, you muſt with a bodkin, pierce two or three holes, to the intent that the Rocket having ſpent himſelfe, your workes which are on his head, may take fire; which holes, prime with a little powder duſt, and then put on his head, with the choaking fitted to your Rocket, which muſt come over the Rocket, in ſuch manner, that the bottome of the greater part muſt come even with the top of the Rocket; which tye faſt to your rocket with threed, and then put in your workes: but before you put in your workes, whether they be ſtarres, or any other workes, you muſt put in a little cotton wooll, being rowled in powder duſt, to the end your ſtars may fire, and likewiſe may blow out: which having done, put in your ſtarres, or other workes, and if you make more than one tire (as you may doe of your ſtarres) then muſt you put more cotton rowled in powder duſt amongſt them, or betweene every tire, to the end they may all take fire; then take your cap ſo provided as I have formerly ſhewed, and fill the hollow place with cotton, becauſe it is light, and likewiſe will fire quickly: which being fitted, paſte it cloſe to the top of the coffin, in ſuch manner, that it may ſtand very upright; then muſt you fit on your ſticke, for the peaſing of your Rocket, which ought to be about eight lengths of your Rocket without the head. You muſt get the ſmootheſt and lighteſt you can, ſuch as basket makers uſe; which when you have got, you muſt make very ſtrait, and then cutting one ſide of it, flat at the great end, make two notches on the round ſide, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided that the one be differing from the other, ſo much as is betweene the choaking of your Rocket, and the end of the vent; becauſe if you ſhould tye it upon the vent, it would looſen the powder, and ſo cauſe it to breake in the firing. Now that you tye not the wrong end of your
<pb facs="tcp:177062:13"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>fig 3.</head>
                     <figDesc>diagram of how to choke a rocket</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:177062:14"/> Rocket uppermoſt, as ſome fooliſhly have done, for want of better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, you muſt alwayes tye the end downewards, which is choaked, and with a piece of ſtrong thred tye it faſt to the lower notch, juſt about the choaking, ſo ſhall you be ſure your ſtickes ſhall not fall off, neither will it indanger the hurting of your rocket. When yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have tyed that, then proceed to the tying of it higher, which as I ſay, muſt be ſomewhat high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r than the top of the vent, and let your ſticke come even with the top of your rocket; which having done, peaſe your rocket, which muſt be after this manner. Lay it on your finger two or three inches or more from the mouth, and if you finde the ſtick be too heavy, cut it ſhorter, till you finde your Rocket to ballance your ſticke, for the ſticke being too heavy, cauſes your rocket to ſlugge, and being too light, it makes a rocket fall before he is halfe up: theſe things being provided, you have your rocket ready to be fired, which muſt be after this manner.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The manner of firing Rockets, with the deſcription of a ſtaffe for the firing of them.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Rovide a long ſtaffe with a pike at one end, which muſt be thruſt hard into the ground, and a three legged ſtaffe with a hollow hoope at the top, to let this long ſtaffe ſlide up and downe, to the end that having rockets, whoſe ſtickes are longer than your ſaid ſtaffe, yet by raiſing it through the ſaid iron hoope, you may make it foure or five foot longer than it would be ſtanding on the ground. Now this long ſtaffe muſt have a ſliding peece cut with ſeverall points, which muſt be neere the top; and at the bottome there muſt be a ring of wyer, to let the ſticke goe through, which muſt be made likewiſe to ſlide up and downe; ſo thruſting the ſmall end through the ſaid ring, your rocket will reſt upon that part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, which muſt be juſt oppoſite in a ſtraight line, ſo open the mouth of your rocket, and pull out the end of your cotton wicke, and with a peece of match, faſtened in a Linſtocke, give fire to the ſaid wicke, and by degreees, you ſhall ſee it fire your rocket; which being well ordered, will mount very ſtraight and high: now having ſhewed the whole order of compoſing a rocket, with the firing of the ſame, I will ſhew you an order for making of your ſtarres, and other workes which are neceſſary for the heads of your rockets; and firſt of all I will ſhew you the making of divers ſorts of ſtarres, with their compoſitions; and ſince wee cannot make them without the compoſitions, I will firſt ſet downe the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, and then proceed to the manner of making them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:177062:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Divers Compoſitions for ſtarres.</head>
               <p>A Compoſition for ſtarres of a blew colour, with red.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake of powder mealed,</hi> 8 ℥</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Salt peter,</hi> 4 ℥</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sulphur vive,</hi> 12 ℥</item>
               </list>
               <p>Meale theſe very fine, and mixe them together with 2 ℥. of aqua vite, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/2 ℥ of oyle of ſpicke, which let be very dry before you uſe it.</p>
               <p>Another Compoſition which maketh a white fire and beautifull.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take powder,</hi> 4 ℥</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Salt peter,</hi> 12 ℥</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sulphur vive,</hi> 6 ℥</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Camphire,</hi> ⅓ ℥</item>
               </list>
               <p>Meale your ingredients, and mixe them; now to powder your Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire, you muſt dip your peſtle in oyle of Almonds, or ſuch like oyle: you muſt not uſe your wooded peſtle for this, becauſe that oyle will ſoake into it, which is an enemy to ſome workes; therefore take a braſſe peſtle and morter, and dipping the peſtle in oyle of Almonds, put it to your Camphire, and ſo ſtirring it by degrees, it will powder; which when you have done, keepe it very cloſe from ayre, till ſuch time as you uſe it, otherwiſe the Camphire will loſe his ſpirit, and become of no uſe.</p>
               <p>Another white fire which laſteth long.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take powder,</hi> 4 ℥</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Salt peter,</hi> 1 <hi>l</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sulphur vive,</hi> 8 ℥</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Camphur,</hi> 1 ℥</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Oyle of peeter,</hi> 2 ℥</item>
               </list>
               <p>Meale thoſe which are to be mealed, very fine, and mixe them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the former directions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:177062:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The manner of making the beſt ſort of ſtarres.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow having ſet downe the compoſitions for ſtarres, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth to know how theſe ſtarres are made, which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers waies, but I will ſet you downe onely two waies both which are very good, ſo that you may take your choyce. The firſt is this, you muſt make little ſquare pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of browne paper, which fill with your compoſition you intend,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Figure</hi> 4. N. G.</note> and ſo double it downe, rolling it till you make it ſomewhat round, about the bigneſſe of a nut or bigger, according to the ſize of your rocket; you may put in a dozen on the head of a ſmall rocket; when you have made them up in this forme, you muſt binde them round with ſmall thred, which done, draw through a cotton wicke prepared for priming, as hereafter ſhall be ſhewne.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſort are made after another manner, which is thus; you muſt have a rowler, as big as an ordinary arrow, which ſhall be to rowle a length of paper about it, and with a little mouth glue, or paſte, paſte it round; ſo have you a hollow trunke of paper, which you ſhall order af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner. Fill it by little and little with your ſmall funnell, ſtill thruſting it very hard, till you have filled it to the top; which done, cut it into ſhort pieces, about halfe an inch in length; then having in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe either hot glue, or ſize mingled with red lead, dip one end of your ſhort pieces, to the end, that both ends of your ſtarre fire not, and alſo that it may not blow out; which being ſo finiſhed, ſet to dry till you uſe them, and then putting the other end into powder duſt, you may put them on your rocket, in one or two tier; alwaies provided, as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that you put in powder duſt betweene every tier, to the end they may all fire; thus have you the manner of making your ſtarres, the formes whereof you ſhall have deſcribed hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Priming for Rockets.</note>The priming before ſpoken of, is made after this manner; take oyle of Camphire, and ſoake ſome cotton wicke in it, then take it out being moyſt, and rowle it in fine powder duſt, which having done, you ſhall hang it up till it be thorow dry, ſo have you prepared a very good pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, which muſt be kept cloſe from ayre, till ſuch time you have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, otherwiſe the ſpirit of the Camphir will decay.</p>
               <p>The deſcription of the ſtaffe for firing of Rockets.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>The long ſtaffe to riſe through the ring.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B B B <hi>The three legd ſtaffe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>The ring or hoope of iron for the long ſtaffe to ſlide thorow.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D <hi>A ſcrew to ſcrew faſt the long ſtaffe being raiſed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E <hi>A piece of iron filed with notches to hang the Rockets on.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F <hi>The ring of wyer to put thorow the ſticke, which may be raiſed higher, or put lower, as occaſion proffers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G G <hi>The deſcription of two ſtarres, with the priming,</hi> K, <hi>and the binding</hi> L.</item>
                  <item>H <hi>The deſcription of the trunke, or caſe, which is to be f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lled with your ſtar mixture, and ſo cut into ſhort pieces, as you ſee repreſented by the figures</hi> 1.1.
<figure>
                        <pb facs="tcp:177062:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                        <head>fig 4th</head>
                        <figDesc>diagram describing how to create a report and the staff for firing a rocket</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:177062:16"/> 
                     <hi>where the uper part repreſents the open end, and is marked with</hi> M, <hi>and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der part which is glued, is repreſented by the letter</hi> N, <hi>ſo have you the ſtarres wholly deſcribed.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> The manner of making ſilver and gold raine.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow I will ſhew you the order for making of golden raine, which is after this manner; you muſt prouide ſtore of Gooſe quils, which hauing, you muſt cut off the quill as long as you can leaue it, and cut not off the other end, but leaue it cloſe as you ſee preſented by the letters O P. Figure 4. where O repreſents one filled, and P one empty. The receit which you make your golden raine, muſt be the ſame which you make your rockets of one ounce, which is to 1 l. of powder, 2 ℥. of coale duſt: now hauing filled many of theſe quils, as I haue ſhewed you, they muſt be put on the head of your rocket, with the open ends down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to the end they may take fire ſo ſoone as your rocket is ſpent, and ſo ſhall you ſee appeare a ſhower of gold, which by ſome is called golden raine: the like way may you make ſiluer raine, filling your quils with the mixture preſcribed for your white ſtarres, and uſing them in the ſame manner, you ſhall ſee them fall downe like a ſhower of ſiluer, which is called ſiluer raine; and thus much ſhall ſuffice to be knowne for this ſort of worke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> How to make Fiſgigs, which ſome call Serpents.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow I will ſhew you to make another ſort of work, which we call Fiſgigs, or as the French name them, Serpents, which are made as followeth. You muſt provide a ſmall mould, of ¼ of an inch diameter, which muſt bee made without a needle, which when you have, you muſt make your caſes, as you make for your rockets, choaking them ½ an inch from the end, which ſhall ſerue for occaſion as it ſhall bee prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered; when you haue made your caſes, fill them three inches with pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der duſt, and then choake him, and after put in a little corne powder, to the end that your Fiſgig hauing plaied a while to and fro, hee may breake and giue a report; the uſe of the making ſo deepe a mouth at your firſt choaking is, that you may fill it with your ſtarre mixture; ſo that put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting diuers of them on the head of a large rocket, they will firſt appeare like ſo many ſtarres, and when the ſtarres are ſpent, taking hold of the powder duſt, they will run wrigling to and fro like Serpents, and after a while they will giue ſo many reports, which will giue great content.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177062:16"/> There are many works which are made of theſe fisgigs, which wee will ſpeak of in their places.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> How to make the reports or breakers.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OW I will proceed to ſhew the manner of making re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports to place on the head of a rocket; you muſt make a coffin of the ſize of your rocket of one inch, but you muſt rowle your paper a great deale thicker, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent your report may be the greater; alſo in choaking, the mouth muſt bee left very large, to the end that on oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion you may fill it with ſtarre mixture; now when you have made divers coffins about three inches and better in length, you muſt leave a ſmall vent at the choaking, the bigneſſe of an ordinary wyer, which you muſt ſtop with a little paper, while you fill the coffin almoſt full, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in halfe an inch of the top, with good corn powder, turning down foure or five folds of paper, choak it cloſe at the top, and binde it round with thred, ſo you have your reports ready, againſt ſuch time you come to uſe them; which muſt be done in this manner: firſt bee carefull to pull out your ſtopple, which having done, fill the mouth with your ſtarre mixture, and ſo faſten him on the top of your rocket, alwayes putting a little paper about the top of your rocket, and in it put a little powder duſt, and ſo ſet on your report, and tie it faſt on, with the mouth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the head of the rocket, ſo that the rocket having ſpent himſelfe, you ſhall ſee a large ſtar appeare, and when it is neere the ground, you ſhal heare the report; the order thereof you ſhall finde deſcribed in the fourth figure.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Is the report ready finiſhed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>The rocket with the report on the head.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>The report faſtned on the head of the rocket.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>The paper to faſten the report to the rocket, which muſt firſt bee tied to the rocket, and likewiſe to the report.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8 <hi>Repreſenteth a fisgig finiſhed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>9 <hi>The choaking, as I have ſhewed, which muſt bee ſilled upward with corn powder.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>10 <hi>The mouth of your fisgig, which upon occaſion you may fill with your ſtarre mixture, to put on the head of your rockets.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>11 <hi>Repreſenteth a fiſgig, with a bladder, which muſt be tyed on to the head of them, in ſuch manner, that the neck of the bladder may go into the fisgig, and ſo be faſt tyed, that they ſtirre not; the uſe of them is, only to fire in your hand, (for being fired with a little powder duſt in the mouth of it) and ſo caſt away from you, it will fly to and fro without ceaſing, till it hath ſpent it ſelfe; and by reaſon of the bladder which is tied to it, it will not ſtick faſt to the ground, as others do which have no bladders.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>12 <hi>Repreſenteth a cracker faſtned to the top of a rocket, ſo that the rocket having ſpent himſelfe, it taketh fire, and maketh many reports; the manner
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177062:17"/> of faſtning him is thus; you muſt firſt tie on your rocket, leaving the ſtick ſo much higher than the top, as will ſuffice to tie on your cracker, which muſt be tied about the ſaid ſtick, in ſuch manner, that the noſe of it may come into the head of your rocket, which being primed with ſome powder duſt, will take fire.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Repreſenteth a rocketh with ſeverall works, whether ſtarres, or ſerpents, and muſt be with a large coffin on the top, with his cap.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 <hi>Is the coffin, which as J have ſhewed you, muſt bee ſomewhat bigger than your rocket.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7 <hi>Is the cap, which muſt be taper.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>13 <hi>Sheweth the faſtning of the ſtick, which muſt not bee higher than your rocket, beſide the large coffin.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>All which I have formerly deſcribed, with the form and manner of making them, and their ſeverall uſes; ſo that I have fully layd down the whole order of finiſhing a rocket for the ayre. Now it reſteth to ſhew what other works may bee done by the ſayd rockets, which are many; for all ſorts of Fire works for pleaſure, do wholly depend upon them, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the water bals: and to proceed, I will firſt deſcribe unto you the order of making the runners on the line, which muſt bee done in manner following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> How to make a runner on the line.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV muſt provide a ſmall rocket mould, which muſt be halfe an inch or more, with rowlers, and rammers, according as I have deſcribed, ſave only that your mould muſt have no needle, nor your rammers hollow; when you have provided them, make up your caſes, after the form which I have ſhewed you, ſome longer, and ſome ſhorter, which muſt be uſed as followeth; your ſhort ones muſt be beaten up to the top, which muſt not bee above foure inches; your longer, which muſt bee 5 ½ inches, muſt bee likewiſe filled foure inches high, and the reſt to be filled with corn powder within halfe an inch of the top,<note place="margin">Receipt for runners.</note> which muſt be choaked cloſe, and tied up; the receipt for theſe ſorts muſt be only fine powder duſt.</p>
               <p>Now when you have driven them as is ſhewed, you may proceed to the finiſhing of them, which muſt be in this manner; you muſt rowle a peece of paper about the head of your ſhorter rocket, (which muſt be left open to give fire to the next) which paper muſt be five inches broad, and being rowled on, you muſt firſt try if the mouth of your other roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket will eaſily go in, which when you have done, draw forth your other rocket which you tried, and binde your paper faſt to the top of your ſhort one, in ſuch manner, that foure inches may remaine hollow above the top of your rocket, which is to be filled with powder duſt, about two
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177062:17"/> inches high; then put in your longer rocket, (with the mouth inward) ſo farre as it may touch your powder duſt; and tie the paper faſt about the choaking, as you ſhall finde deſcribed in the fift figure; after you have done this, proceed to the putting on of your cane, which muſt bee after this manner; you muſt firſt provide canes of ſuch bigneſſe as will fit your line, and cut them three inches, long, or ſomewhat better, and then notch them with three notches, which when you have ſo provided, firſt tie it to your longer rocket which is to fire laſt, and then doubling them together, (in ſuch ſort that the noſe of the firſt come farther out than the tayle of the ſecond) tie it to them both; the reaſon of this is, becauſe otherwiſe, if it were tied to them both together, and not to one ſeverally, ſo ſoon as the firſt were fired, the cane will grow ſlack, and often fall off, and never make his return; and againe, if you ſhould not put the mouth of the one farther out than the tayle of other, it would fire your other rocket, and ſo make a confuſion: therefore that you may the better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what I have ſhewed you, I have ſet down in this fift figure, the whole order of finiſhing a runner for the line.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>Is the ſhort rocket.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>Is the longer, which muſt be beaten foure inches with powder duſt, and one inch with corn powder.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C C <hi>Your two rockets joyned, the mouth of one to the tayle of the other, in ſuch ſort, that there may be two inches between them.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D <hi>The coffin of paper which joynes thoſe two together, and muſt bee filled with powder duſt, lightly put in.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E E <hi>The rockets doubled, with the cane tied on.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F <hi>The cane, which muſt be three inches long, or more.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G <hi>The cord that paſſeth thorow the cane.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>H <hi>A peece of cork on the end of the line.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> The manner of firing your runner.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OW having thus finiſhed your runners, you muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide a line, which may bee a hundred yards, or more, as your ground will permit, ſo faſtning your cord at the fartheſt of your diſtance, provide a peece of board or cork, with a hole of the bigneſſe of your line, which muſt bee put on the end of your line, to the end that your rocket may not reſt againſt any thing that may hinder it in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trogade motion; alwayes provided, you ſope your line very well, for feare of firing: then put on your runner at the other end (with the mouth of the rocket towards you, which muſt bee primed with powder duſt) and pull your line very ſtraight, which is a great help to the running of a rocket, ſo faſtning your cord, you may fire your runner, which being well ordered, will run to the fartheſt of your line, making his return, with a report at laſt; ſo have you finiſhed the runner.
<pb facs="tcp:177062:18"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="illustration">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>fig 5th</head>
                     <figDesc>diagram showing runners, wheels and ground wheels</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:177062:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> How to compoſe a wheele.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OW I will ſhew you the order of compoſing a wheele, which is a prime work, being well ordered; of which ſome are movable, and ſome immovable: of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, ſome move horizontall, and ſome verticall, which is toward the zenith: and firſt of the movable wheele. You muſt provide a wheele of ſuch diameter as you pleaſe, which muſt be made into ſquares, according to the circumference of your wheele, and to proportion your wheele into a juſt number, you may allow five inches or better for every ſide, ſo that your wheele being 14 inches diameter, the circumference will be as 7 to 22, which is 44 inches circumference; ſo being divided by 5, there will bee 8 ſquares,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Figure</hi> 5. N 1.</note> or more properly, 8 ſides, which will every one containe 5 inches and 3/10, which is the cord of 45 degrees; theſe ſides muſt bee hollowed with a groofe fitting your rockets, and at the ends of every ſide it muſt bee filed with notches, to faſten your binding that it ſlide not, when you binde faſt your rockets; the form whereof you ſhall finde in the fift figure N 1.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>Sheweth the</hi> 8 <hi>ſides.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>The places of faſtning.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>The ſcrew which faſtneth the wheele to ſome poſt.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Note alwayes, that as your wheele doth increaſe in diameter, ſo you muſt increaſe in the proportion, for that rocket which forces about a wheele of 14 inches, will not force a wheele of 18 inches; nor that roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket which forceth one of 18 inches, will not force one of 24 inches; but that you may come to a neere proportion, I will ſatisfie you ſo neere as I can; firſt ſeek the diameter of your wheele, which imagine to bee 18 inches, I take the third thereof, which is 6, ſo that your rocket for 18 inches diameter, muſt be 6 inches long, and your wheele of 24 inches diameter, will require rockets of 8 inches; yet as your wheele encreaſeth, you may alter this proportion by dividing it into more ſides.</p>
               <p>Now having provided your wheele, with your rockets of a juſt ſize, you ſhall proceed to the finiſhing of it, which muſt bee after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; you muſt joine your rockets one to another, in ſuch ſort as I ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you for your runners, that is, with the mouth of the one to the top of the other, and ſo proceed till you have faſtned ſo many as will ſerve your wheele, alwayes leaving ſo much ſpace between each rocket, as may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to come round about your wheele, without breaking any; which when you have done, proceed to the tying of them on to your wheele, which muſt be ſo ordered, that you tie them where the notches are, to the end they faile not in firing, by ſliding off. In tying the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> on you muſt provide that you leave a little diſtance between the firſt and the laſt, which muſt be parted with a bolſter of paper well ſoaped, to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:177062:19"/> end that the firſt fire not the laſt, and ſo cauſe a great confuſion. Now for the manner of placing them, it is according to the workmans plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which muſt be either horizontall, or verticall; for the horizontall wheele you muſt provide a poſt faſtned in the ground, and ſcrew your wheele to the top of it; for the verticall, you muſt ſcrew it on the ſide of the poſt, ſo having fired them, you ſhall ſee one run parallell to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon, and the other to the zenith, as you ſhall ſee deſcribed in the fift figure.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>N 2 <hi>Repreſenteth the horizontall wheele.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>N 3 <hi>Repreſenteth the verticall wheele.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>There are many other works which do wholly depend upon the wheele, of which I will ſet down ſome few.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> How to make a ground wheele.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere I will declare unto you the manner of making a paire of wheels to run upon a plain horizon; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide two wheels, (ſuch as are ſpinning wheels) of one bigneſſe, which muſt bee faſtned to a ſmall axeltree, in ſuch manner, that they may not move about the axeltree, and on the middle of the ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltree faſten a fire wheele, which let bee ſo much leſſe than the other, that it touch not the ground, ſo that being faſt upon the ſame axeltree, it cannot run unleſſe it carry the other with it, which being ſet on a plain horizon, will run a great way without ceaſing: now that you may make it return, you may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide your wheele in ſuch manner, that it may have rockets on both ſides, ſo that one ſide being ſpent, it may give fire to the other, which being faſtned with their mouthes the contrary way, will make a return with a ſwift motion.</p>
               <p>The form of theſe ground wheeles you may ſee repreſented in the fift figure, N 4.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A A <hi>the two wheeles faſtned to the axeltree.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C C <hi>the axeltree on which the three wheeles are all faſtned.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>the fire wheele, which is repreſented of a leſſer diameter than the other two.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:177062:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Another manner of ground wheeles.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is another kinde of ground wheeles, and that is made ſo, that the wheeles may move about the axeltree; but this ſort is not moved about by a wheele, in regard the axeltree muſt ſtand ſtill, but it is made after this manner; you muſt make your axeltree ſomewhat broad about the midſt of it, and in that place you ſhall boare two holes, into which you ſhall put two rockets, which muſt bee ſo cloſe one to the other, that they may almoſt touch, and muſt bee ſo joined together, that one having ſpent himſelfe, the other may take fire, after the manner of your line work, to the end that being fired, it may run firſt one way, and then the other taking fire, may make his return by a ſecond motion: now the rockets which you put into this place, muſt alwayes bee proportioned according to the bigneſſe of your wheele, which if you perform according to the direction, you ſhall have your deſire.</p>
               <p>The form of this wheele is expreſſed in the fift figure N 4.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A A <hi>the two wheeles being looſe upon their axeltree.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B B <hi>the axeltree in which the rockets are put.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>the place for the two rockets to be faſtned, which muſt be ſo ordered, that the mouth of one may joyne to the tayle of the other.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>It is eſpecially to be noted, that theſe wheeles muſt run upon a very plain horizon, ſuch as the place for the game of Pall Maile at St. <hi>Iameſes,</hi> or ſome other very ſmooth place; by reaſon that after the firſt firing of a rocket, his violence is over, and ſo a ſmall thing will ſtay him.</p>
               <p>There are alſo ſundry ſorts of wheeles, which do perform divers offices; ſome for diſplaying of a Coat of Armes, and others for ſetting of divers circular works, ſome of them I will ſpeak of; and firſt I will ſhew the manner of making a horizontall wheele, which with one firing ſhall give divers reports, and ſhall ſtand fixed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:177062:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> The manner of making a fixed wheele, which ſhall give divers reports.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV muſt firſt get a wheele turned by ſome work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which muſt be two foot in diameter, (or as you pleaſe to augment or diminiſh your work) which muſt have a groofe turned out of the upper ſide, of halfe an inch wide, and likewiſe as deep; to which groofe you muſt have a peece of wood ſo fitted, that it may juſt ſlide in, which peece of wood muſt have ſo many ſmall holes bored in it as you will have reports about it, alwayes provided, you ſet them not too neere together, becauſe the firing of one may not beat down the other; when you have thus provided your wheele, make a conveyance or hollow trunck of paper which will iuſt fill it, which muſt bee filled with ſome of your ſlow mixtures for ſtarres, and then putting on the cap of wood ſo fitted with holes, and made very faſt with glew, pierce every hole into your hollow conveyance, ſo that putting a quill into eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, they may take fire, and to the ſaid quill faſten a report, ſo ſhall you have a peale of Chambers placed in a ſmall roome, which being once fired,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Figure</hi> 6. A.</note> will follow in order till the whole train be ſpent. The form you ſhall ſee expreſſed in the ſixt figure marked A.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> How to make a fixed wheele which ſhall caſt forth many rockets into the ayre.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is likewiſe another ſort of wheele not much unlike to the former, which ſhall give fire to divers rockets ſtanding circular, the order differs nothing from the former, only you muſt make a hole for every ſtick to paſſe thorow, and therefore it muſt be made ſomewhat broader, which will effect the ſame as the other doth, by conveying fire from one rocket to another, till they bee all ſpent; the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for this conveyance ought to bee very ſlow, wherefore I adviſe you to take this enſuing, which is both ſlow and ſure.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Roch peter,</hi> 8 ℥</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sulphur vive,</hi> 4 ℥</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Camphire,</hi> ½ ℥</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fine powder duſt,</hi> 2 ℥</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:177062:20"/>
               <p>Meale theſe ingredients very fine, and incorporate them, adding ⅛ ℥ of Linſeed oyle, and ⅛ ℥ of oyle of peter; theſe oyles muſt be dropped in by degrees, and ſo wrought up, till you finde your mixture bound like dough, which if you performe well, will bee both ſlow and ſure.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Figure</hi> 6. B.</note> The forme of this wheele is expreſſed in the ſixth Figure, by the letter B.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> How to make a fixed wheele, which ſhall caſt forth divers Fiſgigs, and likewiſe as many reports or breakers.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a wheele to bee turned, with a groofe on the top to put in your conveiance of paper; then fit on a peece of wood, as I have formerly ſhewed you, with ſmall holes to put in quils, which are for the firing of your reports, and muſt bee placed round about the uper part of your wheele; and on the ſide thereof, ſhall be made diuers holes of the bigneſſe of your Fiſgigs, (which ſhall be ſo pierced thorow to the paper convei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) thoſe fiſgigs that are placed round on the ſide, &amp; the reports on the top, one traine ſhall fire them all, and in firing, you ſhall ſee all the Fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gigs flying round about, one after another, as the fire paſſeth to them; and for every Fiſgig which paſſeth out, ſhall bee fired a report, ſo that there ſhall be a continuall motion untill the whole traine bee conſumed: the forme of this wheele is repreſented in the ſixth Figure, by the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter G.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>G <hi>Repreſents the wheele finiſhed, with Reports and Fiſgigs.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>R R <hi>Repreſents the reports, placed on the uper part of the wheele.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F F <hi>Repreſents the Fiſgigs placed round on the ſide of the wheele.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> The manner of making a wheele which ſhall runne two waies, which is, forward and backward.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a wheele to be made, ſo that the rockets may be placed on each ſide, with a hole thorow one ſide, which ſhall ſerve for a vent, paſſing from one ſide to the other, then place your rockets firſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one ſide, provided that the laſt rocket be placed over the ſaid hole, and boring a ſmall hole in one ſide of that rocket, put in a cotton wicke for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and let it come through your wheele, to the mouth of another rocket, which ſhall bee turned the contrary way; ſo that the wheele having finiſhed his revolution one way, may take fire
<pb facs="tcp:177062:21"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>fig 6th</head>
                     <figDesc>diagram showing fixed wheels</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:177062:21"/> on the other ſide, and ſo make a retrograde motion: and as you doe this, ſo may you after the ſame manner, make a wheele which ſhall runne di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, and continue twiſe ſo long as another of the ſame bigneſſe, which is by placing the rockets the ſame way on both ſides. The forme of this is expreſſed the 6 Figure, by the letters D and E.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>D <hi>Repreſents the wheele with Rockets placed on the one ſide, the laſt roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets having a vent, to paſſe through to the other ſide.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E <hi>Repreſents the ſaid wheele finiſhed with Rockets on both ſides.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> The manner of compoſing a wheele, which having finiſhed his revolution, ſhall repreſent a Coat of Armes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ake a wheele of ſome light board, ſo that it may be without any ſpoakes, and upon one ſide of it, let be drawne, that Coat of Armes you intend to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent, then boare ſo many holes in the wood, as may conveniently ſtand on the traced lines, then on the other ſide, neere the top, ſhall a place bee made, which may containe your rockets, with a hole pierced thorow where the laſt rocket muſt reſt. This being done, place your rockets round about, ſo that the laſt rocket may be placed on the vent which muſt bee primed carefully, to paſſe thorow to the other ſide; having placed on the rockets, fill thoſe holes on the other ſide with ſome ſlow mixture, ſuch as is for your ſtars, or the like, then cover it over with paper, and put in ſome powder duſt to fire it, and to break the paper, which being done, ſope it well over for feare of ſome ſparkes lighting on the paper before the appointed time of firing, ſo have you a wheele ready which you muſt put on an axeltree, ſo that it may ſtand verticall, and then firing it, you ſhall have your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, for ſo ſoone as the wheele hath ſpent his moving worke, it will giue fire to the other ſide; and then ſtanding ſtill, you ſhall ſee a perfect Coat of Armes in fire. Figure 7. A. B.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>Repreſents that ſide of the wheele which hath the Rockets placed on it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>Repreſents the Coat of Armes, in which the round ſpots ſignifie the places to be filled with a ſlow mixture, which muſt bee moiſt, to the end it keepe cloſe in.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:177062:22"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>fig 7th</head>
                     <figDesc>diagram showing coat of arms in fire and antique figures moved by rocket</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:177062:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> How to repreſent a Coat of Armes in fire, which having burnt a ſmall while, the ſaid Coat ſhall appeare in his perfect colours, and ſhall continue ſo a long while.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt cauſe a board to be made foure ſquare, of what dimenſion you pleaſe, which let be ½ an inch thicke, and cauſe a Painter or ſome drafts man to traſe out what Armes or other figure you pleaſe, upon the ſaid board; alſo let there be another which ſhall bee an inch and ½ thicke, and of the ſame breadth, which faſten to the other with ſome ſmall tackes, till you have boared ſo many holes as you have occaſion for, which ſhall behalfe an inch aſunder, and likewiſe halfe an inch boare; then boare your holes thorow your inch board, and let them enter an inch into the thicker planke, then make foure ſquare holes (one at each corner) in the thicker planke, to receive foure ſquare pieces of wood, which muſt be an inch ſquare, which glue faſt into foure holes oppoſite to the other in the thinner planke, to the end it may ſlide to and fro; then faſten an iron rod in the midſt of the thinner, ſo that it may come thorow the thicker planke, and be faſtened to a piece of wood, which may turne upon a joynt; to the end you may draw the thinner ſquare neerer as your fire conſumes, and muſt draw it too foot at leaſt; then provide a ſmall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of two foot long, and upon it rowle ſo much paper, till it fill your ſmall holes exactly, then fill ſo many as you have holes already provided in your ſquare, and put them thorow the thinner piece, and the ends thereof into the thicker, which let be glued faſt into the bottome of that, ſo that they may ſtand very faſt, and likewiſe let them paſſe ſo eaſily tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the other holes, that the board may ſlide nearer or further, to or from the fire, at pleaſure; then fit a piece of paſt-board, ſo that it may come cloſe about theſe rouled lances, and may fit as exactly as the board doth at the other end; and let this come within halfe an inch of the firing end, then prime them all with quicke powder duſt, and cover it over with paper, which having performed, you are ready againſt ſuch time as you have occaſion to fire it, which muſt be after this manner, obſerving which ſide the winde is; ſtand on that ſide, and fire it at the lower corner, ſo that by the helpe of the winde, you ſhall have it all fire at once; which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving burnt a while, will come to the paſt-board and fire it, ſo that falling away, there will be repreſented a Coat of Armes in colours, cloſe to your fire, which may be drawne in by one ſtanding behinde, ſo that it ſhall ſeeme alwaies to be ſtanding in one place, and the light not to grow ſhorter till the laſt. The forme of this frame is preſented in the ſeventh figure C D.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>The frame without the ſcutcheon or letters.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>The backe ſide of the frame, with an iron rod paſſing thorow it, and faſtened
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177062:23"/> to the other part, and the moving part which ſlideth to and fro as occaſion proffers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D <hi>The frame finiſhed ready to put in your lances.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F <hi>Repreſents the face of the frame, or thinner board.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G <hi>The inner part of the fixed piece, with holes boared in each alike, to put in your lances of rowled paper, filled with ſlow compoſition.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIV.</hi> How to repreſent an antike dance, by the helpe of fire, which ſhall move in a circular forme.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a board to bee made of two foot ſquare, ſo that one ſide of it may bee hollowed, (or grooved) to lay your rockets in; then cauſe another board to bee made of the ſame largeneſſe, ſo that it may ſit cloſe on the other, the rockets lying betweene, and in the center of the ſame board, place a braſſe ſocket, which muſt paſſe thorow the other for the center pinne to enter into it; then place your antike figures on the top of the ſaid board, with wiers paſſing thorow both; to the end they may be turned about in their motion, by certaine pinnes placed in another board, which muſt ſtand fixed; ſo that moving about the ſaid board, the pinnes take hold of the wiers which come thorow, and turne them backward and forward; but in regard of the extraordinary vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of this motion, it will teare all in pieces, unleſſe you have a great care in making all things to runne very exactly, which muſt bee tried be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you come to uſe it. The order of this is repreſented in the ſeventh Figure by the letter E.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A B C D <hi>The bottome board, which ſtands fixed with a ſocket to put on a long pole, and hath a ſmall pinne ſtanding at each corner.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E E E <hi>The under board which moveth, in which is placed the rockets.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F F <hi>The uper board which is faſtened to the other, wherein the rockets are placed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G G <hi>The wiers paſſing thorow both boards which are faſtened to the foot of each anticke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>H H <hi>The other wiers which ſtand faſt in the fixed board, and are to turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the antickes paſſing by them.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:177062:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> Another way for making an anticke dance, which is not ſo violent as the former.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake one of your large ſort of wheeles, and faſten it on an iron axeltree, ſo that the wheele move the axeltree with his motion; then let there bee a ſcrew filed on the ſaid axeltree, which may bee fitted to a ſmall wheele of tenne teeth or thereabouts as you pleaſe, for the more teeth there is in the wheele, the ſlower it goeth, and eaſier, <hi>et contra:</hi> which wheele let it be ſo faſtened to an axeltree, (on which the board bearing the antickes muſt ſtand) that the fire wheele turning about verticall, may move your worke hirozontall, which will move ſo ſlow, that the fire wheele will be tenne times about, before your Motion will move once about, which being done neatly, will prove a worke of great contentment. The forme whereof is expreſſed in the ſeventh Figure by the letter F.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>The fire wheele placed on an iron axelrree, and made faſt to it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>The ſcrew made on the ſaid axeltree, or filed out of the ſame ſtuffe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>The wheele which the aforeſaid ſcrew muſt be fitted to runne with, which muſt have ſo meny teeth, as you intend the fire wheele ſhall move about for once of your motion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D <hi>The ſquare board on which the antickes ſtand, and is faſtened to the axel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree which hath the wheele.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E <hi>A place for a light to burne ſo long as the worke indureth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F F F <hi>The detentes or pieces which come thorow the board from the foot of each anticke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G G G <hi>Certaine pinnes ſtanding upright in the fixed board, to the end that the others paſſing by may be turned about.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> How to compoſe a Caſtle of fire worke with the manner of placing the workes in a true order.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Repare a Caſtle of wood, or plate, of what large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe you pleaſe, the which ſhall bee made foure ſquare, with round towers and battlements, and on the top or inner part of that worke, let there bee a leſſer tower of the ſame faſhion, with a Vane on the top, or ſuch a like Figure, which having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, let there be a place made cloſe to the battle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or within one inch of them, to lay your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veiances, (which let be of braſſe) which is for your reports, which muſt be placed betweene each battlement, and ſhall have little pipes of braſſe to give fire to each report, which muſt be ſcrewed into the great convei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177062:24"/> which conveiance let be filled with your compoſition for rockets of 1 l. which is one pound of powder to 3⅓℥ of coale duſt; and by this meanes you ſhall have them all fire in order, without any confuſion; which having ſpent it ſelfe, ſhall give fire to another conveiance, which ſhall be placed further in, with a ſtrong wall betweene, ſo that the fire of one doe not offend the other: the uſe of this conveiance is to place divers rockets on, ſo that they may fire one after another, and ſhall take fire as ſoone as the reports are ended. Now for the foure large towers, you ſhal provide foure pieces of wood, turned and fitted to ſlide in exactly, and ſhall have divers ſmooth holes boared round thorow the out ſide of your tower, and the wood, till they meet with the hollow which paſſeth from the top to the bottome, or within an inch, which hollow ſhall bee one inch and a halfe diameter, and muſt be filled with a very ſlow mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, (to the end it may continue as long as the worke is a burning) then place ſome Fiſgigs round in thoſe little holes, ſo that the mouths may be inward and primed, which will take fire one after another, and flye out on every ſide of your Caſtle, which will give great content: for the manner of firing this, I could wiſh, that it were firſt fired at the foure uper towers, and that through one of the corners, may bee a hole, which may goe to the uper conveyance, that ſo thoſe reports may fire next, and at the end of that conveyance ſhall be another to paſſe downe to the lower tier of reports, and at each corner of that conveyance ſhall be a hole to paſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe lower towers, ſo that by that time all the reports are fired, the towers ſhall be all on fire; then at the end of that conveyance, (as I ſaid before) let your conveyance for your rockets bee placed, which taking fire orderly, will conclude the worke. Theſe and the like are for the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of princes and great perſonages, rather then for the vulgar. The forme of this Caſtle is laid downe in the eight Figure by the letter A.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>B B B <hi>Expreſſeth the angles of the lower tower.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C C C <hi>The angles of the higher tower.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D D <hi>The conveiance that fires the reports.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E <hi>The conveyance paſſing to the rockets.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F F F <hi>The Fiſgigs placed round each angle.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G G <hi>Reports placed on the battlements.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>H H <hi>Rockets placed farther in with a wall betweene.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP: XXVII.</hi> How to repreſent divers motions in a Caſtle of fire-worke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a frame to be made, placing thereon two Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, that they may ſtand about twelve foot diſtant one from another; this frame muſt bee ſo ordered, that it may bee hollow underneath, which being done, let the dores of thoſe Caſtles bee placed the one oppoſite to the other, at each end of the ſaid frame, and juſt within each doore, let there bee a
<pb facs="tcp:177062:24"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>figure 8</head>
                     <figDesc>diagram showing a castle of fireworks with moving figures</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:177062:25"/> rowler of wood, foure inches diameter, which ſhall have iron pevikts or points to runne upon, that they may runne the more eaſie; and let thoſe roulers be put full of ſmall pinnes, and a girt put round about them, to the end that the rowlers moving circular, may draw the girt in a ſtraight line, then placing ſome antike Figures on the girt (ſo that they may move about with it) place your fire wheeles upon the axeltree of each rowler, providing another rowler at each end to make it ſlide more eaſily; ſo firing the ſaid wheeles, you ſhall ſee the antikes come one out of one doore, and the other at the other doore, meeting in the midſt; and when they come at the contrary end, they make a returne with their heads downeward, and come up againe at the ſame doores they went firſt out of, which will continue running, ſo long as the fire wheeles continue. And when the wheeles ſtand ſtill, the reports ſhall goe off on each tower one againſt another, which ſhall be done after this manner: let one of the ſpoakes of both your wheeles be hollow, and alſo part of the axeltree, which let be filled with powder duſt, and the rocket which fires laſt, ſhall be placed over that ſpoake which hath the vent, with a piece of cotton wicke to fire it, ſo will it runne downe thorow the axeltree, which (as I ſaid) muſt be hollow, and muſt have paper paſted over it, ſo that as ſoone as the fire comes there, it breakes thorow the paper, and fires a traine which is laid round about it, which traine paſſeth to a ſtanding convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, which goeth up to the battlements, and ſo giveth fire to thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports; which having paſt each corner, the lower tower ſhall fire as it paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and from thence paſſe to an inner conueiance, which ſhall fire ſo many rockets, as may be well placed about it; this being well and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed, will give great content. The forme whereof is expreſſed in the eight Figure, N B B.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>B B <hi>Repreſents the two Caſtles ready fitted with the frame.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A A <hi>The two doores oppoſite.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>The two figures moving forward.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C C <hi>The two fire wheeles which cauſeth this motion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>Repreſents the frame for this motion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D D <hi>The two fire wheeles fixed on their axeltree.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E E <hi>The Roler each wheele is fixed to.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F F <hi>The other Rolers which guide the girts.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G G <hi>The girts paſſing from one roller to the other.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>H H <hi>The figures placed on the girts.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:177062:25"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>fig 9th</head>
                     <figDesc>diagram showing a castle of fireworks with moving figures including an army</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:177062:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> Another way to performe the ſame motions, and will not be ſo violent as the former.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Repare your Caſtle with the frame fitted as the former, onely upon the axeltree of each rowler, let there bee a ſmall wheele with teeth, and likewiſe muſt there bee a ſcrew upon the axeltree of each fire wheele; which muſt be ſo fitted, that they may draw theſe wheeles about, which if they be well fitted, will move them with great facilitie; and whereas the other fire wheeles were placed on each ſide, theſe muſt be placed behinde, or underneath, which you pleaſe, or finde moſt commodious. Now you muſt note that your fire wheele moving once about, moveth but one tooth of your other wheele by reaſon of the ſcrew which drawes him, ſo that if you make tenne teeth in the ſaid wheele, your fire wheele ſhall make tenne revolutions for one of your rowler: by this meanes it will move after a farre more eaſie manner then the former. The manner of this is repreſented in the ninth Figure, A A R.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A A <hi>Repreſents the two Caſtles ready placed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>R <hi>The frame for the motion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B B <hi>Two fire wheeles which forceth the reſt of the worke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C C <hi>The ſcrews faſtened on the axeltree of each wheele, which forceth the rowlers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D D <hi>The two wheeles which are placed on the rowlers, and fitted to the ſcrew which force them.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>P P <hi>The two girts on which the figures are placed.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> How to repreſent the forme of an army of an hundred men mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, which ſhall preſent and fire at one certaine place appointed.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ground of all theſe motions, are wheele workes; wherefore to proceed, you muſt provide a rowler of two foot long or more, which muſt be made and placed as the forementioned, to be drawne by two ſcrewes faſtened to the fire wheeles, in regard of the great weight they are to draw; alſo they muſt be ſomewhat large wheeles, with rockets of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſize, which is five ounces in each rocket, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing about each wheele, 20. or more, which having provided, you muſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177062:26"/> likewiſe get you ſo many figures of ſouldiers, which muſt bee cut by a Carver, and ought to have the joynts looſe of the right arm of each, with a wyer or detent, to come down from the arm to the thigh of each, and likewiſe another, which may move that, and come to the foot; then place theſe on ſeverall girts, ſo that they may ſtand ten in ranck and file, and may be an inch between each, to the end they touch not at the feet, but every file may run in a ſeverall groofe; then placing ſmall peeces in their hands, which muſt bee ready loaded and primed, ſet them going, and within two foot of the end of their march, let there bee a crooked peece of iron ſtuck up, between each file, ſo that they may ſtand iuſt in a ſtraight line, to the end that when the ſouldiers move to that place, the detents or wyers are forced againſt thoſe pins which draw back the arm, and ſo puls the trickers of each Peece in that ranck, ſo that the whole ranck will fire altogether, if they bee well ordered; and as theſe have fired and paſt, another ranck moveth forward to the ſame place, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the ſame; thus continuing till they have all performed the like, which being finiſhed, and all paſt, they ſhall make a ſecond march, orderly without firing. This being well and carefully ordered, ſhall not faile, and will be a very rare work to behold, but will prove extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry coſtly to the owner thereof.</p>
               <p>The form of this you ſhall finde in the ninth figure, by the letter R?</p>
               <list>
                  <item>E <hi>repreſents the whole frame, with all the parts thereof.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F F <hi>are the two fire wheeles, being placed one at each end of the rowler.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G G <hi>the ſcrewes, being faſtned to each fire wheele, which move the two wheeles placed on the rowler.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>H H <hi>the two wheeles being placed at each end of the rowler.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I I <hi>two rowlers, about which the girts do paſſe, which carry the whole body of men.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>K K <hi>the girts on which the figures are placed, each girt having upon it ten, ſo that in the whole there will be an hundred.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>L <hi>repreſents the figure of a man ſtanding in that poſture as hee ought to bee made.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M <hi>Is the detent which is faſtened to the right arme, and is to ſlide on a joynt, being faſtened to the thigh; ſo that it may move the arme.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>N <hi>another detent which moveth the former, as it paſſeth by the pin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>O <hi>the pin which putteth by the ſaid detent as it commeth to it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>q q <hi>the ſaid pins in their right places.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:177062:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXX.</hi> How to preſent muſick playing, (by the help of fire) with anticks dancing.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe an inſtrument to bee made, repreſenting the Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, and to it fit a Barrell ſet with ſeverall tunes, (as I ſhall ſhew you in another Treatiſe hereafter) then let there be a wheele with teeth faſtned on this barrell, and a fire wheele, with a ſcrew on the axeltree, as I have ſhewed before, which ſcrew may be ſo fitted, that as it moves round the barrell one way, ſo it may move another wheele, being placed on the ſide, which wheele ſhall move certain anticks, as the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick playeth. This and many more may bee performed by the motion of wheele work.</p>
               <p>The form of this is expreſſed in the tenth figure, by the letter A:
<list>
                     <item>B <hi>the fire wheele, fixed on the axletree, which moveth a ſcrew.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>C <hi>the ſcrew, moving a wheele placed on the top of it, and another on the ſide.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>D <hi>the wheele faſtned to a barrell ſet with tunes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E <hi>the wheele placed on the ſide, which hath a pinion at the end of the axel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, marked</hi> F; <hi>which carrieth about the wheele</hi> G; <hi>on which there are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced foure anticks: this wheele moveth foure pinions marked</hi> H, <hi>on which is placed foure other anticks.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>I <hi>is the barrell ſet with tunes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>K <hi>the pallats which cauſeth the jacks to move.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L <hi>the jacks which paſſe up to the ſtrings.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>M <hi>a board or frame covering the ſtrings, on which is placed the anticks.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Having ſpoken ſufficiently of the order of motions performed by wheele work, I come now to ſhew ſome things that may bee done on the Line.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXI.</hi> How to make a Dragon, or any other creature to run on the Line, by the help of fire:</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ET your Dragon be made either of paſteboard, or elſe of fine rods, ſuch as your Basketmakers uſe; which muſt bee made hollow, with a place in the belly to put in two rockets, and ſhall bee ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that there may come a ſmall pipe from the tayle of one, to the head of the other; then make a place in the eyes, and mouth, to put into each hole fire, which ſhall be made up in rowled paper, and thruſt in; then on the top of the back let there bee faſtned two ſmall pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys for the line to run in, which being done, your Dragon is finiſhed, to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177062:27"/> firing, which muſt be thus; firſt fire it at the eyes, and mouth, (alwayes noting, that this receipt muſt be ſome ſlow mixture, ſuch as your ſtarres) then fire that rocket which is placed with his mouth toward the tayle of the Dragon, which will make it ſeem to caſt fire from thence, till hee come to the end of his motion; and then on a ſudden, as a creature wounded with ſome accident, ſhall return with fire coming forth of his belly, which being well ordered, will give great content.</p>
               <p>The form of this you ſhall finde in the tenth figure, by the letter B.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>B <hi>repreſents a dragon to bee forced with rockets, which are placed in the belly.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>a place made to put in a rocket, which muſt be put in at the tayle, with the mouth of the rocket outward.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D <hi>is a conveyance from the tayle of that rocket, to the mouth of the next, which commeth out at the belly.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E E <hi>two ſmall braſſe pullees, faſtned in a frame on the back, for the line to run in.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXII.</hi> Another way for making a fiery Dragon to paſſe on the line with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of fire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the former Chapter, I ſpake of a Dragon of a ſmall ſize, of a foot in length, or thereabout; now I come to ſpeak of thoſe of a greater magnitude, which cannot ſo eaſily bee forced with fire, in a ſtraight line, without ſome artificiall help; for Art muſt bee alwayes as a handmaid attending on Nature, to help her in her work; therefore having prepared a large dragon, you muſt make divers hollow truncks of wood, within the body, which ſhall bee to caſt out fire, and on a ſudden divers ſmall bals of fire, other times a great number of ſmall fisgigs. Now to make this run on the line, you muſt have a hollow trunck faſtned on the back, between the wings of your dragon, which muſt bee ſomewhat bigger than your cord, with a ſmall hole thorow each end; the uſe of thoſe ſmall holes is, to faſten a ſmall cord, which muſt be ſo faſtned, that one end thereof muſt bee faſtned at the head of the Dragon, and ſo paſſe over a pulley; (which pulley ſhall bee faſtned at the end of the line) and returning thorow that hollow trunck in the back, it ſhall be put over another pulley at the other end of the line, and ſo making a return, ſhall be faſtned to the hole in the hinder part of the trunck. Now one of theſe pulleys ſhall have a handle or winch to turn it about, which ſhall cauſe the dragon to move, and ſhall be a help to the drawing of it backward and forward at your pleaſure; after this manner you may form many works on the line, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe cannot be done. The form of this is ſet down in the eleventh figure, by the letter A.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177062:28"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>fig 10</head>
                     <figDesc>diagram showing antique figures dancing to music using wheel work and a dragon moving on a line</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:177062:28"/>
                  <item>A <hi>repreſenteth the dragon ready finiſhed, with all his works.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B C <hi>the manner of the hollow trunck which the cord muſt paſſe thorow.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>the place for faſtning of a ſmall cord, which muſt paſſe over the pulley, marked</hi> D.</item>
                  <item>D <hi>the manner of faſtning that pulley which muſt bee at the further end of the line.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>o o o o <hi>the manner of the paſſing of the ſayd line which is thorow the hollow trunck, and ſo over the pulley marked</hi> E, <hi>and then faſtned to the other end of the trunck marked</hi> G.</item>
                  <item>F <hi>a handle or winch belonging to one of the pulleys which maketh the dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon move forward and backward, as occaſion profereth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>H H <hi>the great line on which the dragon paſſeth, and is only for keeping it ſteaddy in the motion.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIII.</hi> How to repreſent <hi>S. George</hi> fighting with a Dragon in fire on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving prepared your figures artificially made, you muſt make a h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llow t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nck thorow the body of each fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to paſſe thorow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> likew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe for a ſmaller lin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to draw them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from each other; which m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt bee faſtned in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is manner: at the breaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he dragon let one end of one cord be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which ſhall paſſe thorow the body of the George, and returning it about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley at the oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r end, faſten it to the back of the George, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the breaſt of the Georg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>her cord be tied, which ſhall paſſe thorow the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a trunck on the back, and ſo returning about a pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley at that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be pulled ſtraight, and faſtned to the tayle of the dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you turn that wheele, the George and dragon will runne furiouſly at each other; and when you pleaſe you may cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to make a ret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat and come on againe divers times; but in all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> forget not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> your line extraordinary well, and likewiſe have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> not too heavy above the line, but that they may hang <hi>equ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wiſe they will turn their heeles upward, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a great diſgrace to the work and workman: there might bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tten upon this ſame ſubiect, but to the ingenious, I think it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y may order their work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> according to their own fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>e is the ground of the matter. The manner of this is repr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> eleventh figure, by the letter B.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>C <hi>repreſening the George.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D <hi>the dragon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E <hi>the ſmall line faſtned to the head of the dragon, and paſſeth thorow the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the George.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177062:29"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:177062:29"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177062:30"/>
                  <item>
                     <figure>
                        <head>fig 11th</head>
                        <figDesc>diagram showing dragon moving on a line and fighting Saint George</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:177062:30"/>
                  <item>F <hi>the pulley which guideth the ſaid line.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G <hi>the place of faſtning the other end of that line.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>H <hi>another line faſtned to the breaſt of the horſe, which paſſeth thorow the hollow trunck of the dragon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I <hi>the pulley about which it paſſeth, and is faſtned to the tayle of the dragon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>K <hi>the place of faſtning the ſaid line to the dragon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>L L <hi>the great line which guideth theſe two figures.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M <hi>the winch or handle faſtned to one of the pulleys, and is for the moving them forward or backward.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIV.</hi> How to make a trunck of fire, which ſhall caſt forth divers fire bals.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Rovide a trunck of foure inch boare, and two foot long, with a hollow place in the bottom, of two inch boare, &amp; as much deep, to the end it may be put on a ſtrong poſt; let there be a bottom left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two boares, which ſhall be two inches thick, ſo that there will be twenty inches left for your work, which ſhall bee filled as followeth; firſt fill it with corne powder one inch, then put in your ball, which ſhall be five inches and a halfe, and round about it put powder duſt, till you come to the top, then fill it two inches and a halfe with ſlow mixture, and on that two inches of corn powder: then put in another ball, and after it ſlow mixture, which ſhall be filled to the top, and ſo reſerve it for your uſe; note that you muſt turn three places for arming of it, which muſt be done either with iron hoops or elſe with cords, to the end the violence of your corn powder burſt it not; your upper ball ſhall be made after this manner: Having made ready a caſe of canvas, fill it with this mixture following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>l. of ſalt peter.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>½ <hi>l. of powder duſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>¼ <hi>l. of ſulphur vive.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 ℥ <hi>of camphire.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>1 ℥ <hi>of oyle of peter.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Mix theſe very well, till it become ſomewhat tough, and then fill your ball, and arm it, leaving foure vents, into which you ſhall put foure ſmall ſticks, till ſuch time you have coated; the manner of coating is, to dip the ball in a mixture of pich, roſin, tallow, and ſulphur, but this is for bals of longer continuance; the coating for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his ball ſhall be as followeth;</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:177062:31"/>
               <p>The receipt for coating,
<list>
                     <item>½ <hi>l. of pitch.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>¼ <hi>l. of verniſh.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>1 ℥ <hi>of ſulphur vive.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 ℥ <hi>of powder duſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Melt your pitch and ſulphur, and then poure in your verniſh and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der duſt, and while it is hot dip in your ball, and then caſt a little fine powder duſt over it, and ſo let it coole a little, and then dip it lightly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and ſo you have it ready; when you uſe it, pull out your foure ſticks out of the vents, and fill them with powder duſt, and ſo put them in. The lower ball which is laſt fired, ſhall be full of ſtarres, with pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der duſt intermixed, to break the ball, theſe ſhall be primed with cotton wick made of purpoſe, to the end it may not fire the bal til it be up a good heighth, and then to break into a ſhowre of ſtarres.</p>
               <p>The receipt of the compoſition for the trunck.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <hi>l. of roch peter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>¼ <hi>l. of fine powder duſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>½ <hi>of ſulphur vive.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 ℥ <hi>of camphir.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>1 ℥ <hi>of linſeed oyle.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The forme of this trunck is repreſented in the twelfth figure by the letter A:
<list>
                     <item>A <hi>repreſents a trunck ready finiſhed, with two bals.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>B <hi>the ball which lieth uppermoſt, and is filled with ſlow compoſition.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>C <hi>the lower ball, which is filled with ſtarres,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>D <hi>the ſlow mixture at the top of the trunck.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E <hi>the corn powder to ſend forth the upper ball.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>F <hi>the ſecond lay of compoſition.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>G <hi>the powder for ſending forth the lower ball.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>o o o <hi>three places left for arming the ſaid trunck.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>H <hi>the bottom of the trunck, which muſt be two inches thick.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>I <hi>a place left to put in a poſt of wood for it to ſtand on.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXV.</hi> The manner of making a Club, which being fired, ſhall caſt forth divers ſmall works, or fisgigs.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a peece of wood to be turned of foure inches diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, boare it one inch and a halfe from the top toward the bottom, only leaving a bottom of an inch thick, and likewiſe a place underneath to put in your club ſtaffe, the length of this trunck may be eighteen inches; then draw a circular or ſpiral line, from the top to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, which let bee in the manner of a ſcrew, every thred being an inch and a halfe aſunder, and in that line boare ſmall holes, (of the bigneſſe of one of your fisgigs) till you come within a quarter of an inch of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:177062:31"/> of each hole; and then pierce it with a ſmall piercer, till you come to the ſoule of the trunck. Having done this, make ſmall wyers fit to each hole, which let be faſtned, ſo that they may ſtand oppoſite to the ſaid holes, within two inches off from each hole; the uſe of them is, to keep your fisgigs more upright and ſteaddy, which otherwiſe would bee apt to fall out, by reaſon they muſt bee put in very ſlack, or elſe they would not ſo eaſily come forth, when they ſhould, then load your trunck with the ſlow mixture appointed in the former chapter (for a trunck) and put in your fisgigs, priming each, and likewiſe each hole, and ſo fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it at the top, you ſhall finde them come forth one after another, as your trunck burneth downwards, which ſhall ſcatter abroad after a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed manner. The form of this you ſhall ſee in the twelfth figure, by the letters E I.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>E <hi>repreſents the form of the club without the wyers on, or any other work.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I <hi>is the ſaid club ready finiſhed with all his work.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>K <hi>the wyers placed for to ſtay each fisgig in his place.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>L <hi>the fisgigs placed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M <hi>the place of firing.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>N <hi>the club faſt put into the bottom.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVI.</hi> Another ſort of club, which being fired, ſhall give many reports.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Rovide a club like unto the former, but let not the holes be boated ſo big, but only that a ſmall quill or pipe may go in for a vent to every breaker, then having boared your holes at proportionable diſtance, cut ſo many hollow groofes with a googe or halfe round chiſell, and fit them to your breakers of paper, and place ſo many reports round about it; your reports or breakers for this work ſhall bee made as followeth; upon a rowler of halfe an inch, rowle ſo much paper till you make it an inch thick, and better, choaking it cloſe at one end, then fill it an inch and a halfe with good piſtoll powder, choaking it at the other end, ſo that it be very cloſe at each end; then pierce a ſmall hole in the middle for a pipe to enter in, which muſt bee filled with powder duſt, and put into the ſmall holes of your trunck, very cloſe, then pitch them well round about, and poure pitch all over, that the work may not be ſeen; and likewiſe that it may hold your reports cloſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; this pitch likewiſe when the fire commeth to it, will eaſily fire, and make a very furious light, which will give great content. The form of this is repreſented in the twelfth figure by the letters O and V.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>O <hi>repreſenting the club without the reports placed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A <hi>the groofes to put in the reports, with a hole in the middle of each groofe to put in the quill.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>R <hi>a report with a quill ready to be placed in the club.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177062:32"/>
                  <item>
                     <figure>
                        <head>
                           <hi>figure</hi> 12</head>
                        <figDesc>diagram showing club, jack in a box, and sphere types of fireworks</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:177062:32"/>
                  <item>q <hi>the manner of the quill which muſt bee put into thoſe ſmall holes to fire the reports.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>V <hi>the club finiſhed, with the reports placed in it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B B <hi>the manner of the reports as they are placed in the ſaid club.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVII.</hi> Another, which I call Iack in a box.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE order of making this is after this manner; provide a box of plate, of what largeneſſe you pleaſe, which let be ſix inches deep, with a ſocket at the bottom to put in your ſtaffe, then putting in a quantity of corn powder or powder duſt, (in the bottom of the box) you ſhall fill it with fis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gigs, or ſerpents, leaving a place in the middle for a cane to go thorow to the bottom, which cane muſt be filled with ſlow receipt, in which you ſhall put a quantity of camphir, but no oyles, in regard of the narrow paſſage it hath to burn, without any other vent; then put your cane down, leaving it an inch above the box, and take a peece of thick paſtebord, cutting a hole for the cane to paſſe thorow, and glew it cloſe to the cane, to the end the fire paſſe not thorow before the appointed time; this paſtebord muſt bee of ſufficient breadth to cover your box quite over, then put it on a ſtaffe, and light your cane, which will appeare only like a candle, and after a pretty diſtance of time you ſhall heare a ſudden noyſe, and ſee all thoſe fisgigs flying ſome one way, ſome another. This toy hath given great content to the ſpectators. The form of this is ſet down in the twelfth figure by the letters B C D.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>B <hi>the box without any thing in it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>the fisgigs placed in the box.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D <hi>the box finiſhed, with a cane paſſing thorow to the bottom.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVIII.</hi> How to repreſent the Sphere, moving in the ayre, without any other ſupportation.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a Sphere to bee made ſomewhat light, and on the horizon place your rockets, and in the zenith or upper part, let there bee a pinne paſſe thorow the meridian, with a ring faſtned to it, to hang it by; this muſt bee faſtned to a large Kite, ſo as the Sphere may hang ſix foot under it, then faſten a match of cotton to the noſe of the firſt rocket, and light it, which having done, raiſe your Kite, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:177062:33"/> by ſuch time as it is at the higheſt, the rockets ſhall take fire, and ſhall cauſe it to make divers revolutions in the ayre; you may place the midſt of this ſphere full of lights, which will ſeeme very ſtrange. The manner of this is repreſented in the twelfth Figure, by the letters K and S.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>K <hi>Repreſents the Kite which is ſupported by the ayre, and to which the ſphere is faſtened.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S <hi>The ſphere with all his circles, the rockets being placed about the horizon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>H H <hi>The horizontall circle about which the rockets are placed!</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIX.</hi> How to repreſent the ſphere, with divers circles, ſome moveable, others fixed.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a ſpheare to be made, either of wood or mettall, the outward circles repreſenting the meridian circle with the horizon, the next within ſhall repreſent the Collurs with the equinoctiall, likewiſe the tropicks and zodiacke, whoſe poles ſhall be 23 degrees ½ from the poles of the world; by which meanes the eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke ſhall bee excentricke to the equinoctiall, (which ſhall be expreſſed) ſo that faſtening rockets about the equinocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, and placing two ſmall lights in the zodiacke, the one repreſenting the Sunne, the other the Moone: you ſhall ſee them move about the earth, (which is placed in the midſt of the ſpheres) according to the rules of <hi>Ticho Brahe,</hi> and ſhall be according to their naturall manner of motion, which is continually riſing and ſetling in an oblique motion to the hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon and meridian, which alwaies ſtand fixed, and the reſt moving on the poles of the equinoctiall, although the eclipticke bee framed from its owne poales. The forme of this is repreſented in the twelfth Figure, by the letter T.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>M <hi>The fixed Meridian.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A A <hi>The Horizon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E E <hi>The Equinoctiall.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E E <hi>The Eclipticke with the Sunne and Moone placed round.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>P P <hi>The poles or axeltree about which all the inner circles move.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:177062:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XL.</hi> How to make a halfe moone of Rockets to appeare in the ayre.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Rovide a piece of planke of two inch thicke, and turne it to a halfe round, then cut ſo many groves (from the center to the circumference) as you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to place rockets about it, and on the other ſide, let there be rings for every rod to paſſe thorow, of which let one of each bee cloſe to the top, and another neere the end of each rod; and note that the planke muſt be ſo large, that the ends of all the rods muſt meet in the center; then prime each rocket with a quill filled with powder duſt, and put on the top of each groofe, till you have placed your ſemicircle full; then having primed theſe groofes, (which comes from one center to the circumference) paſte paper over them, and ſo let it ſtand till you fire it, which is done after this manner: ſet this ſame at the top of a poaſt, about foure or five foot from the ground, and prime it (at the center) with a little cotton wicke prepared for that purpoſe, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it, you ſhall ſee them take fire all at one inſtant, and ſo will flye cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, in the forme of a halfe Moone. The forme whereof is repreſented in the thirteenth Figure, by the letters A B.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>Repreſents the forepart of the frame, in which one preſents the groofes which paſſe to each rocket.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D D <hi>The quils filled with powder duſt, entring into the groofes with one end, and into the rocket with the other.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>Repreſents the backe part of the frame.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E E <hi>The rings below.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F F <hi>The rings above.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G G <hi>The rockets placed on the frame.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLI.</hi> How to make a caſe of Rockets to riſe at once.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a frame to bee made about two foot ſquare, with ſmall groofes, two inches aſunder, and betweene each groofe, boare holes for your rocket rods to paſſe thorow; you may make tenne groofes, and in each groofe you may place ten rockets, ſo you ſhall haue a hundred rockets in one of theſe caſes, which ſhall fire all at once; there muſt bee a croſſe groofe made in the middeſt, and in the center of that groofe, ſhall you fire it, which ſhall ſuddenly fire all over, being primed with a quicke traine of powder: the charge is great, and quickly ſpent, but it makes a very glorious ſhew.</p>
               <p>The forme of this is repreſented in the 13 Figure, by the letters G D.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177062:34"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>fig 13th</head>
                  <figDesc>diagram of a half moon of rockets, a case of rockets and fireworks of letters, sunbeams, ground and aerial types</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <list>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:177062:34"/>
                  <item>A A A A <hi>Repreſents the ſquare of your caſe which is grooved.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The white ſtroakes ſignifie the groofes which are to be filled with powder duſt, whereon the mouth of your rockets muſt be placed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The other ſpaces expreſſe the holes where your rods paſſe thorow with a hole in the midſt to fire it at.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>Repreſents the caſe filled with rockets, their rods paſſing thorow, and is made long, to the end there may be another board at the bottome for each rod to paſſe thorow, that they may be kept more ſteady.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLII.</hi> How to make letters, or any other figure appeare in the ayre, after the ſpending of a Rocket.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving conſidered of what largeneſſe you will have your letters or figures, make them of paſtboard, leaving a hollow to put in ſmall quils, (which ſhall bee filled with a cleare and ſtrong mixture) then put in your quils, and glue them faſt in; and and ſo have you finiſhed it, till you come to uſe it. There is another manner, which is thus; provide a mould of plate, and cut out what letter you pleaſe in waxe, which having done, ſticke it full of quils in an orderly forme, and put this on the head of your rocket: note this, that theſe are onely to be uſed on very large rockets. The forme of theſe are repreſented in the thirteenth Figure E F.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The forme of the letters, the white ſpots ſignifying the place for ſo many quils filled full of ſlow mixture, to be placed in.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIII.</hi> How to repreſent a figure of the Sunne caſting forth his beames, in fire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a boxe to be made of plate, too inches long, and one inch diameter, which muſt be filled with your ſlow compoſition, and let the head be made with ſmall groofes, croſſing the center, to the end you may lay in certaine ſprings of ſteele, ſuch as they uſe to ſmall Watches. Theſe ſprings ſhall bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſixe inches in length, and muſt be foure, ſo that both ends of each appearing, will make eight, which will make a circular forme, the boxe being the center; now to the end of every one of theſe ſprings, muſt be faſtened one of your ſmall Fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gigs, &amp; then bent up cloſe to the boxe, and ſo put into your coffine at the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:177062:35"/> top of your rocket, with powder duſt and cotton to fire and breake the coffine, which as ſoone as it breakes, the ſprings will caſt forth your Fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gigs, and make them ſeeme like the ſparkling beames of the ſunne, and the mixture in the center will ſeeme as the body of the ſame; this will continue a while, and then you ſhall ſee it breake with divers reports. This I had from a noble Captaine of this City, namely Captaine <hi>Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtar,</hi> who invented the ſame, the forme whereof is repreſented in the thirteenth Figure, by the letters L M.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>L <hi>Being the boxe with the ſprings faſtened to the top, with a Fiſgig at the end of each.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M <hi>The ſaid boxe finiſhed with the ſprings bent ready to put on the head of a Rocket; the mouth of each Fiſgig muſt come downe to the mouth of the boxe, and ſo be put with their mouthes all downewards.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Having ſpoken ſufficiently of workes operating in the ayre, I will ſhew you ſomething which ſhall ſerve for ground workes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIV.</hi> How to make a Rocket which firing it out of your hand, ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually be in agitation on the ground ſometimes, and other whiles about in the ayre.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving prepared a Rocket, with a report in the head, tye it to a bladder, ſo that the end of the Rocket may come to the mouth of the bladder, and binde it over very ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then firing it out of your hand, caſt it away from you, it matters not which way, for it will come to the ground, and by reaſon of the bladder, it cannot ſtay, but preſently rebounds upward, moving to and fro, till it be all ſpent. There is another ſort, and that is a ſmall Rocket put into a bladder, and ſo blowne up round about it, and tyed about the necke of the Rocket. The forme of theſe are repreſented in the 13 Figure, by the letters G H.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>G <hi>The Rocket with the bladder at the taile of it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>H <hi>The Rocket in the bladder.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="chapter">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:177062:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLV.</hi> How to make a ball which ſhall be in continuall agitation on the ground, till the fire is conſumed.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a ball to be made of ſome light wood, which muſt be made ſo, as you may take it aſunder juſt in the midſt, then make on each ſide a hollow groofe to lay in two rockets (joyned together af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of your runners) ſo cloſe up your ball faſt with glue; onely in the place where the two Rockets joyne, ſhall be a groofe, which ſhall be paſted over with paper, that the ſecond rocket firing, may have a vent, otherwiſe your ball will ſerve but once. Then fire it, and you ſhall have your deſire. This is repreſented in the 13 Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure by the letters I K.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>I <hi>Repreſents a part of the ball, as it is ready to place in the Rockets.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>K <hi>Repreſents the ball, with the Rockets placed in, ſo that the other ſide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joyned, makes a perfect round.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C C C <hi>The vents to each Rocket, which being cloſed, muſt have paper glued over them, that they be not ſeene.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVI.</hi> How to make another ſort of Balles for the ground, which will be a long time in their motion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a ball to be made of ſome light wood, and let it bee hollowed, to make it the lighter; then fit in two pieces of wood, ſo that you may make both ſides equall, which pieces of wood ſhall be ſo groofed, that you may lay in ſo many Rockets as may well be contained about it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding that at the end of each groofe or rocket, you may have a vent thorow your ball, then place in your rockets as I have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you for the wheele: which having done, glue them faſt in, to the end, that by the motion of the ball, they may not be diſordered, then ioyne your ball together, and glue it faſt with paper round about it, to the end the vents may be covered, onely leaving one open to fire it, ſo have you this ball finiſhed, which firing, will continue a long while in motion, Figure 36.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>The ball turned hollow with groofes to lay in your rockets.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>The other part of the ball, with the rockets faſtened in.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C C C C <hi>The vents at the end of each rocket.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:177062:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVII.</hi> How to make a Dragon iſſuing forth of a Cave, which ſhall caſt out much fire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Rovide a Dragon of ſome light matter, as wicker rods or the like, which let bee made ſo, that you may put into the midſt of the body, one of your greateſt rockets, and cloſe under the belly let there be a couple of wheeles, which ſhall bee ſo placed in the belly of the Dragon, that no part may bee ſeene, but onely the bottome which comes to the ground; and let the rocket bee ſo placed, that it may with traines fire all parts of the body, as the eyes, mouth, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts; in which you ſhall place divers ſmall workes, which firing, ſhall flye out, and make a very great ſhew, which ſhall burne till all bee conſumed: this Dragon muſt be ſo placed, that he may come forth of a ſeeming cave; which firing on a ſudden, will make a great noyſe, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the largeneſſe of the rocket, and the hollowneſſe of the cave hee comes forth of. The forme whereof is repreſented in the fourteenth Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure by the letter G.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>G <hi>The Dragon ready finiſhed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A <hi>The wheeles on which it muſt runne, which muſt bee hid within the body.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>The rocket placed in the body of the Dragon, which cauſeth the motion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G <hi>The vent which paſſeth to this rocket for the firing.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVIII.</hi> How to make two Dragons to meete each other, from ſeverall Caves, which ſhall ſend forth their fire to each other with great violence.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving prepared two Dragons (both of one ſize and weight) after the manner as I have ſhewed you in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapter; it is requiſite that you know how farre they will runne, then place the Caves at ſuch a diſtance one from the other, that they may meete each other in the mid way, and that you may doe this the more neater, you ſhall have your ground laid with ſmooth boards that they may runne more free, and from the midſt of the walke, to the end of each Dragon; let there be a groofe made in one of the boards, which ſhall ſerve to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey a traine to each, for the firing of them; then you ſhall be ſure, that if you fire it in the midſt, they will both take fire together; alwaies provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you make a conveyance of paper from the board to the taile of each Dragon, or to the mouth of each rocket, which being fired once, they
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:177062:36"/> ſhall meete, and caſt forth their fire at each other with great violence. The forme of this is repreſented in the fourteenth Figure, by the letters A A.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A A <hi>The two Dragons ready to runne.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B B <hi>The two great rockets which forceth them.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C C <hi>The wheeles which each Dragon runneth on.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D <hi>The midſt of their walke, with the groofe to each rocket.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>There are divers other workes which may bee performed after this manner, which for brevity ſake I will omit.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe there are divers motions to bee performed by the action of man, as ſingle duels, to which appertaine the Buckler of fire, and likewiſe the Curtlax or Fauchion, the manner of which hath beene formerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by divers Authors, almoſt in all languages, and therefore will ſeeme more then requiſite to relate thoſe things ſo large as they might be; for what action cannot man performe by his induſtry? and therefore I leave every man to his owne order, onely I will ſhew you the making of one ſort of Bucklar, which as yet hath not beene performed, and likewiſe the Fauchion or Curtlax, and firſt for the Bucklar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIX.</hi> How to make a Bucklar which ſhall caſt forth a hundred Fiſgigs, every one making his report.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a Bucklar to bee made of ſome light wood, which let be about two foot in diameter or more, as you pleaſe, then cauſe a groofe to bee cut in it, from the center to the circumference in a ſpirall or ſerpentine forme, then fill that groofe with one of your ſlow compoſitions, ſuch as hath neither oyle nor gummes, by reaſon the ſume thereof may not offend the Bearers; when you have filled it, fit in pieces of wood, which may have holes to receive a quantity of Fiſgigs, let every one bee two inches aſunder, and let there be wyer rings to every one of your Fiſgigs to hold them ſteady, that they fall not out, till ſuch time they fire, then put in your Fiſgigs, into every hole one, till you come to the center, and then ſhall you have a very great breaker, ſo that firing it at the circumference, every Fiſgig will flye out as the fire comes to it, and will flye againſt his adverſary combatant, till they come both to the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and then will they give a great report, and ſo end. The forme of this is repreſented in the 14 Figure by the letters F G.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>F <hi>Repreſents the Buckler as it muſt be grooved.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G <hi>Repreſents the ſame finiſhed, with the Fiſgigs placed about it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>H H <hi>Repreſents the manner of uſing the ſaid Buckler, with the Fauchion.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:177062:37"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>fig 14</head>
                     <figDesc>diagram of dragon moving out of a cage, dragons confronting each other, buckler and falchion filled with fizgigs</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:177062:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. L.</hi> How to make the Curtlax, Cimiter, or Fauchion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Repare a Curtlax either of wood, or plate, which let bee hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed from back to edge, three inches, and let it bee ſo thick, as it may ſerve for your ſmalleſt fisgigs, then you ſhall have a peece of paſtebord ſo fitted on the back, that your work may be cloſe covered, only holes left for the ends of your fisgigs to come forth; then you ſhall lay in your lances of fire (which is nothing elſe but your ſlow compoſition for ſtarres put into hollow truncks of paper made on an arrow) and between every lance you ſhall put two or three fiſgigs, which ſhall fly out ſo ſoon as the fire commeth to them; having done this, you have finiſhed your Fauchion, which muſt bee fired at the point, and ſo burn downward towards the hilt. This hath been former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet forth by Monſieur <hi>Thybaviel</hi> a French Author, and ſince by divers others. The forme whereof is repreſented in the fourteenth figure, by the letters I K L.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>I <hi>repreſents the Fauchion prepared, with a groofe in the back.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>K <hi>repreſents the Fauchion, with holes to put in the works.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>L <hi>repreſents a Fauchion wholly finiſhed, with the fiſgigs placed as they ought to ſtand.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Having ſpoken ſufficiently of land works, I will come in the next place to ſhew the making of ſome works to bee acted on the water; and firſt of all I will ſhew you the making of the water bals.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LI.</hi> How to make a water ball, which ſhall burn on the water, with great violence.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, having conſidered of what bigneſſe you will have your ball, take the circumference and halfe it, and of that halfe make a circle, which cutting out in ſtrong canvas, ſhall bee halfe a caſe, ſo that ſewing two of them together, they ſhall make a caſe according to your deſire; <hi>For Example;</hi> I have a ball to make whoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ameter is ſix inches, then the circumference (being as ſeven to twenty two) muſt be 18 6/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo the halfe will bee 9 3/7, which muſt bee the diameter of your cloth, and muſt bee made true round, ſo that ſewing two together, and making a caſe thereof, it ſhall bee almoſt ſix inches, which the arming will make good; having made your caſe, you ſhall proceed to the filling of it, which ſhall be done after this manner; you ſhall firſt put in three or foure good
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:177062:38"/> ſpoonfuls of your mixture, and then with a ſtick (made round at one end) force it cloſe together, and ſo continue filling it, and between every filling put in your ſtick, and force it together, rounding it continually in your hand, till ſuch time you have finiſhed it; which having done, ſew it up cloſe, and then arm it with ſmall cord, which is called marling; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you have done that, you ſhall coat it with a quantity of roſin, pitch, and tallow diſſolved, and ſo your ball dipped over in the ſame, providing alwayes that you leave two vents to fire it, which ſhall be pierced a third part into your ball, and muſt bee ſtopped with ſmall ſticks, till ſuch time you come to uſe them, then pulling forth the ſticks, fill the two vents with fine powder duſt, and firing it, caſt it into the water, and you ſhall have your deſire; you muſt alwayes let your ball be thorow fired before you caſt it from you.</p>
               <p>A receipt for this ball.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take</hi> 1 <hi>l. of powder.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8 ℥ <hi>of rochpeter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 ℥ <hi>of ſulphur.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 ℥ <hi>of camphir.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>1 ℥ <hi>of oyle of peter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>1 ℥ <hi>of oyl of linne.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>½ ℥ <hi>of oyle of ſpike.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 ℥ <hi>of colophonia.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The forme of this ball is repreſented in the fifteenth figure by the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters A B.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A A <hi>the canvas ready cut, to be ſewed together.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>the ball finiſhed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C C <hi>the two vents.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D <hi>a peece of cord left to hold it by whilſt you coat it, and likewiſe to hang it up being finiſhed.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LII.</hi> A water ball which ſhall ſhoot forth many reports.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a ball to be made of wood, which ſhall bee in two peeces, ſo that you may joyne it cloſe together at pleaſure; this ball muſt have ſmall holes boared round about it, to put in your quils, which muſt fire your reports; the reports or breakers ſhall bee made of paper choaked at both ends, and primed thorow the midſt; they ſhall bee faſtned round with pitch, and ſo covered round about, that no water may paſſe in; you ſhal fil this bal in two halfes, to the end you may force it very cloſe together, and when it is filled, glew it faſt, and arm it well with nealed wyer, then put in your breakers, with a quill
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:177062:38"/> which ſhal enter into the bal, and likewiſe into the breaker; the forme whereof you ſhall ſee in the fifteenth figure, by the letter C. The receipt for this bal muſt be ſomewhat ſlower than the laſt, by reaſon of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vents it wil have, as the reports paſſe away.</p>
               <p>The receipt for this ball.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take</hi> 1 <hi>l. of rochpeter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 ℥ <hi>of powder duſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 ℥ <hi>of ſulphur vive.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 ℥ <hi>of camphir.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>1 ℥ <hi>of linſeed oyle.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 ℥ <hi>of roſen.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>1 ℥ <hi>of oyle benedick.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Powder that which is to bee powdered, and incorporate them well together, and by little and little ſprinckle your oyles, til you have wrought it like a paſte, and then make uſe of it; your quils which you prime with ſhal be filled only with powder duſt, to the end it fire ſuddenly before the quil come to ſhrink up, which wil be with a ſlow mixture.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>the mouth of the ball where it is to be fired.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B B B <hi>the reports or breakers, being made of paper, and filled with corne powder.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C C C <hi>the quils, which are primed with powder duſt, and ſerve for firing the reports.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D <hi>the hollow of the ball, being filled with the ſlow compoſition.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LIII.</hi> How to make a Water ball, which, after a certaine time of firing, ſhall caſt forth divers rockets into the ayre.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Repare a ball of wood, of eight inches diameter, and boare a hole in the midſt (of an inch and a halfe) and let it come within one inch of the bottom, and round about that great hole you ſhall boare eight ſmaller holes of an inch, ſo that they may bee fit for eight rockets; theſe holes ſhall be an inch from the greater, and ſhall all meet in one at the bottom; wherefore you ſhall cut off the bottom of the ball, and fit another to it, which may be ſo hollowed, that your mixture may be conveyed to all the rockets, then faſten on the bottom (having filled it with your mixture) and put in your rockets, with the mouth of each rocket downward, paſting paper round about it, which ſhall bee coated with roſin and tallow, and over each hole where the rockets are placed, let it be ſoaped over the tallow, to the end that being fired, the ſparks may not eaſily take fire of the paper, which otherwiſe would make ſome confuſion; having done this, fit in a peece of wood to the greater boare of your ball, leaving only a ſmaller vent, of halfe an inch, and by this
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:177062:39"/> meanes the fire will come out with more violence, and having ſpent it ſelfe, within one inch of the bottom, it ſhall fire the eight rockets placed about, which by their force ſhall break the paper of each, and aſcend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ayre, a ſmall heighth, and after lie tumbling on the water. This ball is repreſented in the twelfth figure by the letter D.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>the place of firing the ball.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B B <hi>the peece of wood put in to leſſen the vent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>the greater hollow to be filled with the ſlow compoſition as the former.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D D <hi>the bottom, which is looſe, and to bee hollowed to receive part of the ſlow mixture.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E E <hi>the holes boared to put in the rockets, which muſt bee covered with paper.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F F <hi>the rockets placed in, with their mouthes downward.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G G <hi>the place of fitting the rockets.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LIV.</hi> Another ſort of water ball, which ſhall caſt forth rockets at two ſundry times, and after it is finiſhed, ſhall give a great report.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ball ſhall be made after the manner of the other, but ſhall bee a foot in diameter, and ſhall have two circles of rockets placed round about, ſo that the lower circle ſhall be one inch from the higher, and likewiſe ſhall go down into the ball an inch lower, and under that row of rockets there ſhall be placed a breaker of iron, which ſhall bee one inch from the lower tyer, ſo that the ball being fired, ſhall after a certain time, caſt forth a dozen of ſmall rockets, and then continue a while longer, and then in regard of the larger circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of that circle, it ſhall caſt forth twenty, and after that is ended, their fire comming to the chamber of iron, ſhall cauſe a very great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and ſo conclude. The form of this is layd down in the fifteenth fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure by the letter H.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>H <hi>the vent for firing the ball.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I I <hi>the peece of wood fitted to the greater boare.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>K <hi>the hollow of the greater boare filled with a ſlow compoſition.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>L L <hi>the upper tyer of rockets.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M M <hi>the lower tyer of rockets.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>N <hi>the breaker of iron.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>o o o o <hi>the places to put in the rockets, which muſt bee covered with paper well ſoaped, upon tallow.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:177062:39"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>fig 15th</head>
                     <figDesc>diagram of water balls</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="chapter">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:177062:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LV.</hi> Another ſort of ball, with iron chambers, every one caſting forth a ſmall ball.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a ball to be made, of twelve inches diameter, and in the midſt boare a large hole of two inches high, hollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it within, and let it come within an inch of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom; then boare ſmall holes of an inch from the top to the bottom, in a ſpiral line, to put in your ſmal cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, which ſhall be made of iron, each chamber having a broad plate at the mouth to faſten it to the ball; thoſe chambers ſhal be loaden with a quantity of corn powder, and after that a ſmal ball made up in canvas, and primed, as I have ſhewed you for ſtarres, then having filled the large concave with ſlow compoſition, place in your chambers, whoſe touch holes or vents muſt bee juſt at the breech, and ſhal come al in toward the center of the ball, then coat it round with roſin and tallow, and ſo have you this bal finiſhed; the form whereof is repreſented in the fifteenth figure, by the letter A.</p>
               <p>The firſt figure marked F, repreſents the inſide of the bal.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>F <hi>the mouth of it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B B <hi>the iron chambers, as they lie with the touch hole or vent of each cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, at the breech of the ſame.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>the concave filled with ſlow compoſition.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D <hi>a large chamber placed at the bottom: note, that this ball muſt bee made in two peeces, to place in this chamber, and after glewed well, and bound about with wyer.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The ſecond figure marked G, is the bal finiſhed, except the coating.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>G <hi>the vent at the mouth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B B <hi>the reports, with a plate of iron round the mouth of each, to nayle it faſt.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>This bal being thus provided, muſt be after covered with canvas, and then dipped in a mixture of three parts roſin, two parts pitch, and one part tallow, which muſt bee firſt incorporated on the fire, and ſo uſed: this bal may ſerve as wel for ſervice in warre, as for pleaſure or triumph, by putting into each chamber a bullet of lead, and ſo ſhot out of a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter peece.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:177062:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LVI.</hi> There are divers other ſorts of bals, as well for water as for land, and are to be ſhot out of the Morter peece.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND becauſe the Morter peece is often uſed in Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works, I will deſcribe the manner of it, with the uſe thereof, as much as is requiſite to this place: and firſt for the manner; the manner of the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter peece conſiſteth only in his proportions, which are divers, according to the pleaſure of the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; but thoſe of moſt uſe for fire bals, are one and a halfe, and two diameters, in the length of the chaſe, and one diameter in the length of the chamber, with halfe a diameter at the mouth of the chamber; the reaſon of this ſhortneſſe is, that one may come the more commodiouſly to the firing of the ball; the proportion of this peece followeth in the ſixteenth Figure.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>B <hi>is the form of a Morter peece lying on his carriage, the quoyn being made to draw with a ſcrew, as I have made uſe of.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A A <hi>the diameter or heighth of the boare, which is</hi> 4¼ <hi>inches, or</hi> 100 <hi>parts of this ſcale.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A B <hi>the length of the chaſe, and is two diameters, or</hi> 8½ <hi>inches.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B B <hi>the heighth of the chamber, which is halfe a diameter of the ſhot, which is here two inches.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B C <hi>the length of the chamber, which is one diameter of the ſhot, that is foure inches.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C C <hi>the bottom of the chamber, which is one inch, or</hi> ¼ <hi>diameter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D D <hi>the diameter of the trunions, which is halfe the diameter of the ſhot, and is two inches.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D E <hi>the length of the trunions, and is two inches.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The proportion of powder for this peece is 2 ℥ for a ſtone ſhot, and 1 ℥ for a Fire ball.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LVII.</hi> How to make a ball for the Morter peece, which ſhall caſt forth a great ſhowre of ſtars at the breaking.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ball muſt bee made of canvas, and muſt bee ſo propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, that being armed (as I have formerly ſhewed) it may iuſt fit the chaſe of your peece, which being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, you ſhall proceed to the filling of it, which muſt be after this manner; at the bottom of this ball put in an ounce of fine corn powder, and then put in ſome of your round ſtarres well primed, and ſo fill them up cloſe about with powder duſt, ſtill putting in more of thoſe ſtarres, and in the midſt put
<figure>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177062:41"/>
                     <head>figure 16th</head>
                     <figDesc>diagram of balls for use with a mortar</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:177062:41"/> one ſtarre which may be ſomewhat great, ſo filling it till you come within one inch of the top, then fill it up with a ſlow receipt, as I have formerly preſcribed for bals; and ſew it cloſe up, arming it with fine cord, or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line, and pierce a vent in that place where your ſlow mixture lyeth, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies provided you pierce it not too deepe, that your ball breake not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his appointed time: then when you would uſe it, loade your morter piece with one ounce of corne powder, putting after a wadd and tampi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and put on your ball with the vent towards the mouth of your piece: ſo elevating your piece toward the Zenith, you may proceed to the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it, which muſt be after this manner: provide two matches ready lighted, having one in each hand, and firſt fire your ball with one hand, and preſently give fire to your Piece with the other, alwaies holding your head under the horizontall line of your Piece, for feare the blaſt annoy you: this having done, you ſhall ſee your ball mount very high, with a faire taile of fire, and when it is at higheſt, ſhall breake forth into a goodly ſhowre of ſtarres: one of theſe bals will containe almoſt one hundred ſmall ſtarres. The forme of it is repreſented in the 16 Fiigure, by the letter G.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>C <hi>Repreſenting the ball cut in ſunder, that you may ſee the order of the ſtars lying.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E <hi>The great ſtarre in the midſt, with all the reſt placed about it. Note every one of theſe ſtars muſt be primed thorow with cotton wicke, as I have formerly ſhewed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D <hi>The ſlow mixture, which commeth within one inch of the top.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LVIII.</hi> Another ſort of ball for the morter piece, which ſhall caſt forth divers Rockets in the ayre.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ball muſt be made of wood, according as I have formerly ſhewed you, onely it muſt be made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the piece, and moreover the vent which in the other is required to be a ſlow mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in this muſt bee more ſwift, in regard it would otherwiſe continue till it came to the ground, wherefore the mixtute that this ball ſhall be filled with, ſhall be the ſame that your rockets of one pound are, which is 4 ℥ of coleduſt to a pound of powder, and one ounce of ſaltpeter. Theſe muſt be well mealed, and likewiſe muſt be cloſe driven, otherwiſe it will conſume too faſt. This ball may bee made ſomewhat cillindricall, in regard of the length of the rockets to be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in it, as you have made this for to caſt forth once, ſo you may make another to caſt forth twiſe, as I have formerly ſhewed you for the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ball. The forme is repreſented in the 16 Figure, by the letter D.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177062:42"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>fig 17th</head>
                     <figDesc>diagram of fireworks on water in the form of a ship, a mermaid and a castle with dragon and horseman</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="chapter">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:177062:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LIX.</hi> How to compoſe a ſhip of fire workes, which being once fired, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers motions ſhall preſent themſelves.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a mould to be made ſo, as you may take off the upper decke, to place ſome worke; underneath, where you ſhall have a fire wheele placed with a ſcrew on the axeltree; this wheele ſhall bee pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed in the ſterne, and ſhall turne a rowler, on which ſhall be two girts placed, which ſhall paſſe on each ſide of the maine maſt, and runne on to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; in this wheele there ſhall be a hollow ſpoake and axeltree, as I have formerly ſhewed, which ſhall be ſo ordered, that the wheele being ſpent, it may convey fire to a tier of gunnes lying round about, which ſhall be fired with a cloſe conveyance, and having paſſed that, it ſhall take hold of another conveyance, which ſhall give fire to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine rockets, being placed in the bodies of ſome figures repreſenting Mariners, and ſhall be ſo fitted, that they may have a cane joyned to the body to guide them, ſo that they may runne up from the top of the deck, to the top of each maſt: this and many the like may bee performed with great facility. The forme of this is repreſented in the 16 figure A.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>Repreſents the ſhip ready finiſhed, with all things in motion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>The fire wheele which moveth the rowler, and carryeth the girt whereon the figures are placed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>The figures placed on the girt being in motion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D D D D <hi>The tier of guns which fire as the wheele beginneth to ſtand ſtill.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E E <hi>The figures which ſtand ready to runne up the cords; alſo you may ſee ſome in their motion halfe way, and others being got up to the top of the maſts.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LX.</hi> How to make the Siren or Mermaid, playing on the water.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is to be formed divers waies, according to the magnitude of the figure; if you will make one of an ordinary length, which is five or ſixe foot, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed as followeth: Let the body bee made of light rods, ſuch as basket-makers uſe, and in the center of the body, let there be placed an axeltree, having too wheeles comming into the water; yet ſo as they may not be ſeene; theſe wheeles muſt be made hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, to containe a quantity of ſand or water; the uſe of it is to keepe the Sirene upright, and alſo to ſinke it ſo farre into the water as is needfull, and likewiſe to make it goe more ſteady; note that theſe wheeles muſt bee looſe, and the axeltree faſt; in the midſt of this axeltree, place three or
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:177062:43"/> foure great rockets, one by another with their mouthes all one way, yet ſo provide, that there may be ſuch a diſtance betweene each rocket, that there may come a vent from the taile of the firſt, to the mouth of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and from the ſecond to the third, and to the end that it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the longer in motion, you may place divers lights about the body, to make it more beautifull; every of each light extinguiſhing, ſhall give a report, and ſo conclude. The forme of this is repreſented in the 17. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure by the letter B.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>B <hi>Repreſents a Siren on the water.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>The wheeles which are looſe on the axeltree, being hollow, and filled halfe with ſand or water.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D D <hi>The rockets placed in the axeltree which is faſt.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>There are many other workes to be performed on the water, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall art, or the helpe of the hand: ſome of which I will ſhew, the reſt I ſhall leave to the iudgement of judicious workemen in that art; in regard there are ſea fights, which are performed by gallies placed on the water, with the helpe of Mariners acted; and likewiſe Caſtles placed both on the water, and on the ſhoare; all which doe repreſent ſome former ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the like: yet know this, there are many motions, to be wrought by hand, after a more ſecret manner, which will cauſe more admiration, and is done by certaine lines placed under the ſuperficies of the water, the ground of which I will ſhew you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LXI.</hi> How to repreſent a Dragon iſſuing out of a Caſtle, which ſhall ſwimme thorow the water, and be incountred by a horſeman from the ſhoare.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a Caſtle to be made on certaine timber, ſo as it may flote, if it be in a flowing and ebbing water, and let the bottome of the doore of this Caſtle, with the ground plat, be two foot under the horizon of the water (the reaſons follow) and at a foot high within the Caſtle, let there bee a certaine line tyed, which may paſſe thorow the body of the Dragon, and may bee faſtened neere the ſhoare, where you ſhall have a floate likewiſe ſunke ſo farre under water, that the line may not be perceived, then faſten on your Dragon, as I have formerly ſhewed you for the line, but ſo that the head of this may alwaies be above the line, where that was under: then when the time appointed comes, there ſhall be one ready within the Caſtle to fire thoſe parts of the Dragon which is requiſite, which being done by the helpe of thoſe pullies, ſhall paſſe it thorow the water, which ſo ſoone as it preſents it ſelfe, <hi>Neptune</hi> (as being diſpleaſed to ſee ſo monſtrous a creature within his bounds) ſhall come and encounter the ſaid Dragon,
<pb facs="tcp:177062:43"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177062:44"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>page 66 and 67</head>
                     <figDesc>foldout of a diagram combining multiple types of pyrotechnics previously described</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177062:45"/>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:177062:45"/> and at laſt ſhall overthrow him: you may order your work ſo, that which you pleaſe ſhall have the victory, for that which keepeth fire longeſt, is ſuppoſed to have the beſt, and that which is ſooneſt ſpent, to have the worſt. Many rare things may be done in this for the pleaſure of Princes, which are to be acted on the water, which for brevity ſake I omit: onely I ſhall ſhew you the order of compoſing two ſorts of workes, the one to be acted on the land, the other on the water. The forme of this worke is repreſented in the 17 Figure, by the letters C D.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>G <hi>Repreſenting the Castle floating on the water, out of which the Dragon iſſueth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E <hi>The Dragon comming forth of the Caſtle.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D Neptune <hi>comming towards the ſaid Dragon to encounter him.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F <hi>The pully which cauſeth theſe motions by meanes of drawing them to and from each other: the manner of faſtening the line for drawing them, I have ſhewed you before in the</hi> 33 <hi>Chapter.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LXII.</hi> An order for a generall piece of fire-worke for land, and is for the pleaſure of a Prince or ſome great perſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Auſe a frame to be made of wood, which let be eight ſquare, or more properly eight ſided (which is the beſt figure for this purpoſe) and let it bee forty yards from one ſide to the other, there place two Caſtles the one oppoſite to the other, which Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſhall be eight foot ſquare, theſe Caſtles ſhall be fitted with motions, as I have formerly ſhewed you, ſome comming out againſt others, ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on the walles; all which may bee performed by the helpe of large fire wheeles, which muſt be at the leaſt ſixe foot diameter, with large Rockets for the ſame purpoſe, as I have formerly ſhewed you: then on the foure adjacent ſides, you ſhall place foure other wheeles, two run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning horizontall, and two verticall; and on the other two ſides you ſhall place rockets, ſome flying upright, and others circular; at each angle or corner, there ſhall be placed a torch of a beautifull fire and ſlow; ſo much for the ſides: now you ſhall come to fill up the vacuum betweene the ſides, alwaies noting that from one Caſtle to the other, paſſeth a frame of wood, the uſe whereof I have formerly ſhewed, then before the midſt of this frame, there is placed on the one ſide, two ſquare caſes of rockets, and betweene theſe caſes toward the bottome, and ſomewhat before, there is placed anticke motions, and to the angles of each Caſtle are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced two lines, with runners which take fire, and paſſe to and fro; note the end of thoſe lines muſt be perfect wyer, or elſe the fire would burne them, then on the ſame ſide behinde the motions, ſhall ſtand aloft a frame with the Kings name or the like; then on the other ſide of the frame,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:177062:46"/> within the vacuum, ſhall be placed three ſtanding wheeles, whereof the one ſhall caſt forth rockets into the ayre, the other two are for reports and fiſgigs; theſe three wheeles ſhall ſtand in a triangular forme, and ſhall have a frame paſſe from the one to the other; and betweene the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles of theſe wheeles, ſhall be placed two mortar pieces, which ſhall bee to caſt fire bats, with divers workes in them. The manner of this is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in the 18 Figure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LXIII.</hi> Another order for a generall worke, and is to be acted on the water.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving a place appointed for your worke, (which muſt be in ſome ſpacious River) you ſhall ſeeke the moſt convenient place on the ſhoare for pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing a Caſtle, which ſhall bee made to repreſent ſome City or Fort lying on the water; this Caſtle ſhall be furniſhed with all manner of workes, as well fire bals, as rockets, with divers ſmall Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to give a more grace to the worke; this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing provided, you ſhall alſo make another Caſtle on the water, on certain boats chained and lying at anchor, theſe ſhall bee ſet at a reaſonable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the other, about twenty ſcore, or as your place will permit: in this Caſtle likewiſe you ſhall provide workes, as in the other, onely this Caſtle may not be ſo big as that on ſhoare, then you ſhall provide divers ſmall ſhips, which ſhall be ready to make a ſea fight: theſe ſhall be ſo divided, that the greater part may belong to the ſmaller Caſtle on the water, and likewiſe for ſurpriſing that on the land; likewiſe you may have motions paſſing from one Caſtle to another, as I have formerly ſhewed you for the water; amongſt the reſt you ſhall have ſome ſmall fire ſhip, ſuch as I have ſhewed you, which ſhall have divers motions: now there are many actions to be performed by theſe workes, as caſting bals from one Caſtle to the other, with the morter pieces, likewiſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding backe rockets to each other, with divers onſets on each ſide for ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſals, all which I leave to the diſcretion and appointment of the iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious workeman; and becauſe I will not trouble you with prolixity, I will conclude this my Pyrotechnia; onely I will at laſt impart that which is not the leaſt, which is the making of certaine Engines for trying of powder, of which I ſhall ſhew you foure, with the uſe of them in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Chapters, and ſo conclude.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="chapter">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:177062:46"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LXIV.</hi> Of the uſe of certain Engins for the trying of the goodneſſe or ſtrength of powder.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I come to explaine the manner of making thoſe Engins, I will ſhew you the commodiouſneſſe of them, eſpecially in theſe works; for hee that will make a good rocket, muſt be certain of the ſtrength of his powder, which if it bee too ſtrong, will break; if too weak, it will not riſe to that heighth it ſhould; which, I muſt confeſſe, hath been a great loſſe of labour to me, as well as to other men, yet if men will be ſo carefull and take that paines for the trying their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, they may make rockets infallible; therefore I adviſe every man that will work ſure, firſt to take his powder, be it what it will, and allay it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rules preſcribed, then take a quantity of that mixture, and put it into your Engin being exactly weighed to a graine, then drive your rocket, and be ſure to follow the former rules preſcribed in driving your rockets, which being finiſhed, with his works upon his head, you may fire it, which if you ſhall finde to bee too violent, you may allay by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereto a proportion of coale, and ſo try it again, till ſuch time you finde it to be the beſt, then note that proportion for all rockets of that ſize, and ſo do for all others; and if you finde your mixture yet too weak, adde thereto a ſmall quantity of roch peter till you make it of ſufficient ſtrength; and thus doing, you ſhall have a certain and infallible rule for your proportions: I could ſet down the proportions according to my Engins, but that would prove an abſurdity, in regard every Engin may have a greater or leſſer ſtrength added to his ſprings, or the like, as you ſhall perceive in the next Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LXV.</hi> The manner of making the aforeſaid Engines for trying the ſtrength of powder.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE firſt is made in a circular form, with a neck comming from the circumference, which ſerves for a lid to the powder box, which box ſhall bee made to hold the quantity of a dram of powder, or there about, ſo that being covered with the lid, and fired, will blow, according to the ſtrength of the powder, and moving, will turn about a circle of braſſe, which is divided into certain equall parts, and ſo will ſhew the ſtrength accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the part it cutteth; for the greater the degree is that it is blown
<pb facs="tcp:177062:47"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>fig 20</head>
                     <figDesc>diagram of engines for determing the strength of powder</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:177062:47"/> up to, the ſtronger is the powder, and contrary. The form of this is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in the twentieth Figure, by the letter A.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>repreſenting the form of the whole Engin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>the powder box, which muſt be filled to the top.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>the lid, which muſt be put on the ſayd box, it being filled.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D <hi>the circle of braſſe to which the lid is faſtned, which is divided into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and runneth upon the pin E, paſſing thorow the center, with a ſcrew to ſet it harder or eaſier.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LXVI.</hi> Another Engin for trying of powder.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE lid of this ſecond ſort is made to riſe in a ſtraight line, and hath for his guide two ſquare pillars of braſſe, divided into degrees, with ſprings to keep it ſteaddy in this motion; this muſt be made on a ſquare peece of braſſe, with the ſmall box in the midſt, and two ſquare pillars on each ſide, with a peece of braſſe to ſlide up and down by thoſe pillars, and muſt ſerve for a cover for your powder box; this peece of braſſe muſt have ſmall ſprings, which muſt go to each ſide of the ſquare to guide it ſteaddy in the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The form whereof you ſhall finde in the twentieth Figure, by the letter B.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>B <hi>the whole frame, with his parts adjoyned.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>the ſquare plate of braſſe, on which all is faſtned.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D <hi>the powder box, ſtanding in the midſt of that plate.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E E <hi>the two ſquare pillars of braſſe, ſtanding on this foot, and may bee made to ſcrew off and on at pleaſure.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F <hi>the lid to the fire box, which is made to ſlide up the two ſquare pillars.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G G <hi>the ſprings, which are faſtned to the lid, to make it move more ſteaddy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The diviſions</hi> 10, 20, <hi>&amp;c. ſhew of what ſtrength the powder is, for the higher that the lid riſeth, the ſtronger is the powder.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LXVII.</hi> A third Engin for trying the ſtrength of powder.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE third ſort are made ſomewhat after the manner of the former, which is to riſe up ſtraight, only it hath a cover hollow as big as the box, and on each ſide of the cover is a ſmall hole for a wyer to paſſe thorow, and on one of the ſides are little peeces of ſteele or braſſe, ſo fitted, that they will riſe with a touch, and give way to the riſing of the lid, and ſo ſoon as it is paſt, will hold it there, and will not ſuffer
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:177062:48"/> it to paſſe down any further; this I hold to bee the beſt of the three, in regard that the ſprings in the former are ſubiect to grow foule with uſe, and ſo will be very ſtiffe, every time more and more; but this will not. The forme of this is repreſented in the twentieth Figure, by the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter C.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>the foot whereon the Engin ſtandeth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>the powder box, which hath two ſmall wyers paſſing from each ſide to the top, to guide the lid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D <hi>the lid, which hath alſo two holes on each ſide for the wyers to paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E <hi>the ſide which is divided, on which is placed at every degree, one of thoſe peeces to ſlide up and catch the lid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F F <hi>the forme of thoſe catches, being either of ſteele or braſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G G <hi>the two wyers which guide the lid of the box, and muſt bee put into a little peece of braſſe at the top, which may bee ſcrewed higher or lower at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for the ſtraightning of the ſame.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>H <hi>the ſcrew which ſtraightneth thoſe wyers.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LXVIII.</hi> Another Engin for trying the ſtrength of powder by water.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE fourth, and moſt certaineſt way of all, is by water, and is thus; cauſe a ſmall veſſell to be made of braſſe, and very tight, ſo as it may containe a pinte of water; let this veſſell bee made in a cillin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dricall form, and from the top of this veſſell let there bee made a pipe of braſſe, which ſhall turne like the ſiphon, and ſhall have a ſcrew at the lower end, to ſcrew into a box of braſſe; all which ſhall ſtand on a woodden frame: now when you wil uſe this, you ſhal fil this great veſſel halfe ful of water, at a pipe which ſhal come from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, and come up to the top winding, then ſhal there be likewiſe another veſſel underneath for a receiver, ſo that putting a quantity of powder in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſmal box, and ſcrewing it on, it is ready; then fire the powder, and you ſhal ſee it ſend forth a quantity of water, which you ſhall weigh, and ſo keep the weight of it, by this you ſhal know what quantity of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſuch a goodneſſe wil ſend forth ſuch a quantity of water; this I hold to be the certaineſt way, although the moſt troubleſome. The form of it is repreſented in the twentieth Figure, by the letter D.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>repreſenting the veſſell of water, which ſhall be alwayes filled one halfe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B <hi>the pipe of braſſe which paſſeth from the powder box to the veſſell of water.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C <hi>the powder box, being ſcrewed to one end of the ſaid pipe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E <hi>the receiver, to receive ſuch water as is forced out.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G <hi>the pipe which conveyeth that water into the receiver.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F <hi>the bottom being of wood, with a plate of braſſe let into it.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:177062:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
